<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo sermons vpon 1. Peter 5. vers .8. and 9 Wherein is shewed that the diuell is to be resisted only by a stedfast faith, how soeuer he commeth either against soule or body: and that whosoeuer hath once attained the true and liuelie faith, it can neuer be vtterly lost, but he is sure to get the victorie. By M. George Giffard, Preacher of the worde of God at Mauldon in Essex.</title>
            <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112185</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847443</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847443</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01739)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 461:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo sermons vpon 1. Peter 5. vers .8. and 9 Wherein is shewed that the diuell is to be resisted only by a stedfast faith, how soeuer he commeth either against soule or body: and that whosoeuer hath once attained the true and liuelie faith, it can neuer be vtterly lost, but he is sure to get the victorie. By M. George Giffard, Preacher of the worde of God at Mauldon in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Felix Kingston for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: B⁴ C-G.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, V, 8-9 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, 16th century.</term>
               <term>Devil --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12478:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12478:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TVVO SERMONS <hi>vpon</hi> 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>and</hi> 9. Wherein is ſhewed that the diuell <hi>is to be reſisted only by a ſtedfast faith, how ſoeuer he commeth either againſt ſoule or body: and</hi> that whoſoeuer hath once attained the true and liuelie faith, it can neuer be vtterly loſt, but he is ſure to get the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By M. George Giffard, Preacher of the worde</hi> of God at Mauldon in Eſſex.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by Felix Kingſton, for <hi>Thomas Man. 1597.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12478:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12478:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL M. Ioſeph Bainham Eſquire, and to Miſtreſſe Ione Bainham his Wife.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, when J call to minde the reuerent and holy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of that godly Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr both of your name, countrie, and houſe, M. <hi>Iames Bain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> who died moſt conſtantly for the truth of the Goſpell, as we haue his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at large deſcribed in M. <hi>Fox,</hi> pag. 1030. and conſider withall the great mercie of God, in continuing ſtill vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that VVorſhipfull name and ſtocke, the ſame light of faith, and zeale of the truth, and holynes of profeſſion: J no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:12478:3"/>doubt to ſay vnto you, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the holy Apostle wrote vnto Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie, <hi>When I call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the vnfayned faith that is in thee, which dwelt firſt in thy Grandmother Lois, and in thy Mother Eunice, and am aſſured that it dwelleth in thee alſo,</hi> 2. Tim. 1.5. So it cannot be but a great ioy and comfort to thoſe that feare God, to ſee the posteritie of Martyrs, to retayne ſtill the holy faith and profeſſion of Martyrs: not only to be of their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly linage, but of the ſpirituall kindred alſo: not to be next them only in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but to folow them in regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And this example of your owne cloth, as it is vnto vs an occaſion of reioycing, ſo to you it must ſerue, not as a ſpur to pricke you, but as a ſtarre to direct you, and a line to leade &amp; draw
<pb facs="tcp:12478:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>you forward to al holy encreaſe of faith and zeale. That holy man, as he was vertuous in his life, deuoute in prayer, ſound in faith, patient in his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo most of all was he constant and cheerefull in his death: who in the midst of his torments, and out of the raging flames of fire, thus ſpake with a comfortable and heauenly voyce: <hi>O yee Papiſts, behold, yee looke for miracles, &amp; here now you may ſee a miracle, for in this fire I feele no more paine, then if I were in a bed of downe: but it is to me as ſweet as a bed of Roſes.</hi> How ought wee now to honor the memorie of this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed man, and how much are you to praiſe God, that hath giuen you out of your worſhipfull houſe ſo worthie an example and encouragement to all Christian proceeding? J ſaye againe
<pb facs="tcp:12478:4"/>with the ſame Apostle. <hi>Wherefore I put you in remembrance that you ſtirre vp the gift of God in you, &amp;c.</hi> 2. Timoth. 1.6. And J doubt not, but that as it is true generally in the Church: <hi>Sanguis Martyrum ſemen Eccleſiae:</hi> the blood of the Martyrs is the ſeede of the Church: ſo more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in your familie, that it hath been bleſsed of God, and made fruitefull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeaſoned as it were by the blood of ſo holy a man. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>Paſſio Chriſti ſufficit ad ſalutem, paſſio Martyrum contulit ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum:</hi> Christs death ſufficient to ſaluation, the Martyrs death is effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall for example and instruction. You haue both Christs holy paſſion to ſaue you, and this Martyrs worthy exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and confeſſion to instruct you. The memorie of this excellent man gaue me
<pb facs="tcp:12478:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>occaſion to preſent this Sermon vnto you, which came to my hands, which contayneth a profeſſion of the ſame faith for the which he dyed, in you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerencing his remembrance, and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his faith: God graunt vs all the like zeale and holynes in our liues, that wee may haue the like comfort and cheerefulnes in our end.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willer in the Lord,</hi> Thomas Man.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb facs="tcp:12478:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12478:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TWO SERMONS VPON THE 1. Peter 5. verſ. 8. and 9. Wherein is ſhewed that <hi>the diuell is to be reſiſted only by a ſtedfaſt faith, how</hi> ſoeuer he commeth either againſt ſoule or bodie: and that whoſoeuer hath once attained the true and liuelie faith, it can neuer bee vtterly loſt, but he is ſure to get the victorie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>The firſt Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Be ſober and watch: for your aduerſarie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, as a roaring Lyon walketh about, ſeeking who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuour: whome reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith. <bibl>
                           <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>5.</hi> verſe. <hi>8.9.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed Peter an Apoſtle of Ieſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1</note> wrote this Epiſtle to the Chriſtian Iewes which dwelt as ſtrangers diſperſed here and there in ſundrie countries, as in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Aſia, and Bithynia. For the ten tribes were ſcattered of old time, and had dwelt long among the Gentiles in many kingdoms, being caried away by Shalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſer king of Aſhur, out of their owne lande, as wee read 2. King. 17. And of ſomewhat later times manie of the tribe of Iuda and Beniamin
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12478:6"/>were alſo diſperſed among the heathen: ſo that S. Iames wrot his epiſtle in like maner to the twelue tribes which were in the diſperſion, Iames 1. ver. 1. Theſe diſperſed Iewes came vp out of all landes at certaine ſolemne feaſtes, vnto Ieruſalem for to worſhip there according to the law of Moſes and there had they heard the Apoſtles preach Chriſt, as ye may ſee by that which is written Act. 2. and beleeued in him: and vnto them that ſo beleeued S. Iames and S. Peter directed their Epiſtles. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the matters handled in this Epiſtle of Peter, we are to note that the holy Apoſtle dealeth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie about the duties of chriſtian life: as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the times being then full of troubles and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of perſecutions, hee laboureth to make them bolde, patient, conſtant and cheerefull in all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and ſufferinges, which they were to paſſe through to come to the partaking of the heauenly glory with Chriſt. Alſo hee vſeth manie graue and forcible reaſons to mooue them vnto true holineſſe, euen to walke in the vertues of the ſpirit of grace, and to bring foorth fruites worthie of ſo high a calling. But firſt of all he openeth as it were the fountaine and beginning of all good actions in man, that is, how God of his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie had choſen them, and begotten them in Chriſt to bee his children and heires of glory. Among theſe perſwaſions, admonitions, and exhortations of the Apoſtle, this is one which I haue read vnto you, and which I am now to handle. It may bee diuided into three partes: Of which the firſt is an
<pb facs="tcp:12478:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>admonition, or an exhortation, wherby he ſtirreth vp all the faithfull vnto ſobriety and watchfulnes, in theſe wordes, <hi>Be ſober and watch.</hi> The ſecond part ſheweth what cauſe there is to mone all men vnto this ſobriety and watchfulnes, or how much it ſtandeth them euery way vpon, ſeeing they haue ſo terrible and ſo cruell an aduerſary, who conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie ſeeketh their eternall woe and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which is in theſe wordes: <hi>For your aduerſarie the diuell, as a roaring Lion walketh about, ſeeking whom hee may deuoure.</hi> The thirde and laſt parte doth teach howe wee ſhall withſtand him, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, and put him to flight, that ſo wee may eſcape from his cruell tyranny: which is in theſe words, <hi>Whom reſist ſtedfaſt in the faith.</hi> All men may eaſilie ſee, that the matter which wee haue here to deale in, is of the greateſt moment. If a man haue landes or goods, and perceiue that he hath an aduerſary which lyeth in wait, and ſeeketh to depriue him of the ſame, it will mooue him to take heed, and it wil ſet him on worke, to ſeeke all the wayes and meanes hee can to learne how hee may defend and hold his right. If a man do knowe that his enemie doth continuallie ſeeke all oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie and all occaſions howe hee may ſet vpon him vnawares, and with the greateſt aduantages he can, to take away his life: will he not watch and take heed? yea will be not bee glad to learne how he may ſo arme and ſtrengthen himſelfe that hee may withſt and his ſaide cruell enemie when hee commeth? Here is a farre greater matter, not the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12478:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>loſſe of goods or landes, or of this fraile life, but the deſtruction of both body and ſoule in eternall damnation, which is ſought by a very mightie, ſubtill and cruell enemie. I know therefore that ſo many as haue any ſparke of true wiſedom, wil be very attentiue to hearken to this exhortation of the Apoſtle, and willing to learne how they may be kept ſafe from ſo great a danger. For how ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a thing is it, that we ſhould bee ſo carefull to beware of men, that they may not harm vs, which is but in lighter matters, &amp; in the mean time haue no regard how to beware of diuels, which ſeek our eternal wo and miſerie? Hearken therfore (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) vnto this wholſome inſtruction: for nowe will I come to handle euery member by it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be ſober and watch.</hi> Watching to this end that we may keep our ſelues out of danger, is the chiefe and principall matter of this exhortation: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man can bee fit to watch vnleſſe hee bee ſober, hee ioyneth them both together, and ſaith vnto vs, <hi>Be ſober and watch.</hi> It is in vaine to call vpon drunken men to watch, for ſleep will ſoone oppreſſe them: hee that is ſober, hee may watch: <hi>Be ſober therefore</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and watch.</hi> For our further inſtruction in this point, wee are to remember, that there bee two kindes of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, two kindes of ſoberneſſe, two ſortes of ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and two ſorts of watching, the one of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, the other of the minde. Hee that with exceſſe and ryote powreth in wine and ſtrong drinke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he be drunken, his ſenſes are then oppreſſed,
<pb facs="tcp:12478:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>drowſmeſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vpon him, and he falleth into a ſound ſleep, his aduerſary may come vpon him and doe vnto him what he will: this we all knowe to be true. He that keepeth himſelfe in ſobrietie, &amp; is not ouercome with wine or ſtrong drink, but vſeth them moderately, he can, if need bee, watch for to eſchue and withſtand perilles and dangers. Now as the bodie is made drunken with wine, or ſtrong drinke, ſo is the mind oppreſſed and made drunken with earthly cares, with carnal pleaſures, with euil luſtes and vaine delightes, which bring a drowſineſſe vpon it and a dead ſleepe, ſo that the ſpirituall enemie may come vnto it at pleaſure to doe what he will. On the contrary part hee that keepeth his mind ſober touching thoſe cares and pleaſures, ſo that hee is not oppreſſed nor drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them, he can watch, to auoyd the ſpirituall dangers. This then is the thing which Saint Peter doth exhort vnto, that we caſt out cares and vain pleaſures out of our minde, that they make it not drunken, and caſt it into a ſleepe, and ſo into extreame perill, but that it may continue ſober and fit to watch againſt all ſpirituall dangers. Our Sauiour Chriſt doth teach that the heauenly ſeed is choked with cares &amp; pleaſures of this life, Luk. 8 verſe 14. And if any ſhall now demaunde, Doth S. Peter exhort here only vnto that ſobrietie of the mind? or is it his purpoſe to exhort vnto ſobrietie in drinking alſo, together with that other? I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that he requireth both: in as much as a man cannot haue a ſober and watchfall minde which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12478:8"/>doth follow the drunkenneſſe of the body. For ſuch as be giuen to gluttony and drunkenneſſe, or to take pleaſure in pampering the fleſh, their minde is drowned in all luſtes and carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and then cares doe alſo enter, how they may prouide for the filling of thoſe inſatiable luſtes: and ſo their minde is alſo drunken and in a deade ſleep, ſo that they cannot watch for to eſchew any ſpirituall danger. This is the extreame miſerie of ſuch as doe flowe in vaine delightes, that they bee drunken and aſleepe, the diuell may put into them almoſt what he liſt. And therefore our Sauiour Chriſt warning his diſciples to watch for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to iudgment, willeth them firſt to beware leaſt at any time their hearts ſhould be oppreſſed with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe, and with the cares of this life, and ſo that day ſhould come ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly vpon them, Luke 21. verſ. 34.36. Where we ſee plainlie that our Sauiour ioyneth both the bodilie drunkenneſſe, and the drunkenneſſe of the mind together, as making men vtterly vnfit to watch. Then beloued, let vs giue good heed, and follow this wholſome counſell which the holie Ghoſt doth here giue vnto vs by this Apoſtle. If we watch not, we are vtterly vndone, we are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly caſt away, as it ſhall appeare by the next words. We cannot watch vnleſſe wee keepe our mindes from the drunkenneſſe of cares and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pleaſures, and our bodies from exceſſe of wine and ſtrong drink, and continue them ſober. And thus much touching the firſt part.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12478:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Now to the ſecond: <hi>For your aduerſary the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, &amp;c.</hi> If we be not ſenſeleſſe, &amp; voyd of all care, yea euen as ſtones almoſt or blockes, if we be not like mad men, this may mooue vs vnto all ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie and watchſulneſſe of minde, here is ſo fearfull and ſo horrible a danger ſet before vs, if we do not watch, namelie, that our cruell enemie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell ſeeketh about continually, and lieth in waite greedilie to deuoure our ſoules, yea euen to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vs vp vnto eternall damnation in hell. Is it a light matter (beloued) to be deuoured of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell? Is it nothing to goe to hell? we are ſure to fall into his handes, wee are ſure to bee deuoured and ſwallowed vp into the woſull gulfe of hell, if wee doe not learne to be ſober and to watch, and ſo to auoyd him: for if we be drunken and ſo aſleep in mind, he commeth vpon vs, and there is no helpe nor any way to eſcape him. Behold here, what the cares and pleaſures of the fleſh do bring men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that is to ſay, they cannot watch, but their mind is drowned and caſt into a deepe ſleepe, ſo that the diuell commeth vpon them, and taketh them as a praie, ſwalloweth them vp vnto eternall captiuitie. But there is great force in euerie worde to expreſſe vnto vs this danger, and therfore I will handle them particularlie. <hi>Your aduerſarie.</hi> Saint Peter propoundeth vnto vs an aduerſarie: and what doe men looke for at the handes of a deadly aduerſarie, but all the harme and miſchiefe that he can worke them, and therefore each man hath an eie to his aduerſarie, to beware of him, that hee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12478:9"/>catch him not at any aduantage. Now this aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie which is here propounded doth ſo burne in extreame hatred and malice againſt God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all mankind, that it is giuen vnto him as a proper name: for in the Hebrue tongue he is called <hi>Satan,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, an aduerſarie. For he is the aduerſarie, as I may ſay, of aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or the chiefe of all other. There is no way of reconciliation to be ſought with him, there is no truce to bee made, nor yet any mitigation of his cruell furie to be looked for, but we may be ſure of all the miſchiefe and harme that hee can any way doe vnto vs, make full account of that. There is no pittie or mercie with him, neither is he any way to be truſted, for he is a lyar, he is a deceiuer, hee is a Diuell. <hi>Your aduerſary the diuell.</hi> As hee is called <hi>Satan</hi> in the Hebrew tongue, ſo is he in the Greek tongue called <hi>Diabolos,</hi> which we call <hi>Diuell,</hi> it is as much as to ſay, one that doth accuſe, one that with cauillation doth depraue &amp; lay crime. Look what is beſt done, that doth diſpleaſe him moſt: he is nothing but falſhood and lies: as I ſaid, heere is no truſting here is no way or hope of mitigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his cruell rage. But it may bee obiected, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the multitudes of nations and people vpon the earth are ſo many, how can one Diuell put all in danger? for Saint Peter ſpeaketh as it were but of one Diuell. While he is in one countrie, he cannot be in another, and while hee is dealing with one man, another then goeth free. For anſwere vnto this, we are to vnderſtand, that S. Peter ſpeaketh
<pb facs="tcp:12478:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>as of one diuell, not becauſe he is but one: for the holie ſcriptures do teach that there be multitudes, and as it were Armies of Diuels which doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe vs about ſeeking our vtter deſtruction; wee reade in the Goſpell of a legion of Diuelles which did poſſeſſe one man; as it is ſayd, they were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: But S. Peter heere ſpeaketh as of one, becauſe there is but one kingdome of Satan, &amp; one prince of darkneſſe, that kingdome is not diuided, Satan is not diuided againſt Satan, as our Sauiour tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, Mat. 12. They doe all deale in one buſines, one doth not enuy another, one doth not hinder or let another, but further what they can: and ſo they ioyne all together, as if they were all but one Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. The bond which doth tie them togither in this conſent, is that cruell malice and hatred where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they burn both againſt God &amp; man. So God may bee diſhonored and blaſphemed it pleaſeth them by whomſoeuer it be done: ſo men may bee brought to damnation, they care not which of them preuaile moſt. If one of them doe as it were halfe preuaile to caſt downe a man to perdition, and another do finiſh it vp, they contend not who hath done moſt. There needeth no praiſe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation in that kingdome to pricke any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; neither any threatning to the negligent: all are caried with a vehement heat to do their vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. There is no man free then from the aſſaults and temptations of Diuels: they ſeeke to deuoure euery ſoule. Let no man imagine that hee can bee drunken in minde, and ſo lie aſleepe; and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12478:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet be free from danger: He that will eſcape muſt be ſober, and watch, for a multitude of Diuelles compaſſe vs about. It is ſayd further, <hi>As a roring Lyon.</hi> We are very faſt aſleep if this roaring can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not awake vs, and cauſe vs to be ſober and watch, eſpeciallie if we conſider why he is ſaid to roare. It is written Pſal. 104. verſ. 21. <hi>The Lyons roaring after their praie, doe ſeeke their meate at God.</hi> Wherby it doth appeare that the Lyons being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hungrie and greedy, they roare after their praie: and therfore to expreſſe how greedily Satan doth hunt after the ſoules of men, how hungry he is for to deuour them, he is likened vnto a roaring Lyon which ſeeketh his praie. This compariſon ſheweth that hee is verie terrible, for a Lyon is a mighty beaſt, and being ſo hungrie and greedie that hee roareth for the praie, it much increaſeth the terror. The diuel then is here ſet forth vnto vs to be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in as much as he is likened to a Lyon, and verie hungry &amp; greedy in deuouring the ſoules of men, in that he is likened to a roaring Lyon. Who then that is wiſe wil make himſelf dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken in mind with cares and pleaſures, and lie ſleeping when ſuch a terrible enemie ſeeketh to deuour him? And now it may be demaunded, what is the cauſe that the holy Ghoſt doth ſet him foorth vnto vs to bee ſo mighty and ſo terrible? the cauſe is manifeſt, wee are ſecure, we are negligent, we are ready to ſleep, our minds are ouerwhelmed and drowned in all luſtes and carnall pleaſures, as if there were no danger at all: ſuch is our extreame madneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:12478:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>And that is the cauſe why the Scripture in other places alſo deſcribeth the diuell to bee ſo horrible. Saint Paule calleth the Diuels Empires and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the rulers of the darkneſſe of this worlde, and ſpiritual wickednes in the high places. And ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the Diuelles haue their fierie dartes with which they ſeek to pearce through &amp; ſlay the ſouls of men. Ephe 6. ver. 12.16. What a dreadful mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is he ſet foorth to be Reu. 12. Hee is not only likened to a drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo a moſt huge gret one, yea ſo mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous great, that he caſteth forth a floud of waters out of his mouth, &amp; his tail caſteth down the third part of the ſtars of heauen. He is not only a moſt monſtrous great Dragon, but alſo fiery red, burning with hatred, with crueltie, &amp; blood. Full of deep ſubtilties, for he hath ſeuen heads. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mighty, as hauing ten hornes. One that hath as a victorious Prince often conquered the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world, for he hath ſeuen crownes. What a terror is ſet foorth in all theſe, a hungrie roaring Lyon, mightie powers with fierie dartes, a moſt monſtrous fierce Dragon, full of ſubtiltie, crueltie, and power? Is heer any place to be drunken and to ſleepe? doth it not ſtand vs vpon to be ſober and to watch? vnleſſe we account it a ſmall matter to fall as a praie into the pawes of this roaring Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to haue our ſoules pearced through &amp; woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to death with his fierie dartes and to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp into the bellie of this Dragon, and with him to be caſt into the lake of fire, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death. Reuel. 20. ver. 14. O beloued, let vs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12478:11"/>not be ſo dull hearted, when the Lord doth warne vs of ſuch an aduerſary, as to make no reckoning, but be as careleſſe, as if wee had no enemie at all that ſought our woe. Men in deed doe naturally feare and tremble at any ſignes of the preſence of diuels; if he ſhew himſelfe in any vgly forme, they be terrified: and yet neuertheleſſe moſt careleſlie make their owne mindes drunken with cares and carnall pleaſures, falling into a dead ſleepe, ſo that he vtterly ſpoyleth them, and woundeth them to death, and they feele it not. This is euen the courſe almoſt of the whole worlde. O lamentable and wretched eſtate! who can bewaile it ſufficientlie? Howe many thouſand thouſandes haue drunke themſelues ſtarke drunken with the delightes of this world, and as merrie as they bee, are by this roaring Lion deuoured as a praie, and ſwallowed vp by the Dragon? Drunken perſons, eſpeciallie when they be fallen into a deep ſleep, haue no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance of their miſeries: Bee they in debt, or condemned to death, they feele it not, but can laugh: and ſo playeth the drunken world. O how neceſſarie a thing is it then that we bee ſober and watch, to the end that we may eſcape ſuch daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? But it is added further that this aduerſarie goeth about ſeeking whom he may deuour. This doth much yet further increaſe the perill, &amp; ought ſo much the rather to mooue vs vnto a moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſobrietie and watchfulneſſe: this aduerſarie doth continuallie ſeeke all occaſions, and lieth in waite to eſpie all aduantages, how he may deuour
<pb facs="tcp:12478:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>vs as his praie. If a man haue a ſtrong aduerſarie, and one that hateth him ſo deadly that if he could catch him, he would take away his life: and the ſame his aduerſarie be a farre off in another coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and doth not lie in wayte for him, hee may be the more ſecure, hee may ſleepe quietlie. But if hee bee alwayes at hand, and doe in all places dogge him, to eſpie his fit opportunitie to doe him miſchiefe, doth it not ſtand him vpon, if bee make any account of his owne life, to keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſober and watchfull? ſhall be drinke himſelfe drunken and lie downe to ſleepe? The Diuel our aduerſarie goeth about, hee is euer at hand, hee ſeeketh all occaſions how he may deuour vs, is it now ſafe for vs to ſleepe? Men when they ſeeke about and trauell, doe waxe weary, and muſt haue times to eate, and to take their reſt: it is not ſo with the Diuell, hee is very ſwift, hee is neuer weary, hee needeth no foode, nor yet any ſleepe, hee ceaſeth not day nor night for to worke our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. When wee trauell on the day hee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs, when wee lie vpon our beds in the night he dealeth with vs, there is no time that we can be free from him. If hee cannot preuaile at one time, he wayteth for another: if hee cannot ouercome a man in one ſinne, hee trieth him in another: and moſt carefullie he watcheth his fit occaſions, and then he tempteth ſtrongly.</p>
               <p>To bring a man vnto drunkennes, riot, &amp; exceſſe and to ſpend his time in vaine exerciſes, he hath his inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, euen riotous perſons, which are wholy
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12478:12"/>giuen that way, for to draw and to perſwade. Wo be to that man which lighteth into the familiarity of ſuch ſinners that will ſo allure and intiſe him. What a wonderfull force there is in companie for to drawe men vnto euill, cannot almoſt bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: and therefore when Satan hath founde ſuch inſtruments for to ſet vpon a man, hee hath gotten great aduantage. When a man is in place where he may ſecretly commit ſome foule ſinne, as theft or adultery, and the occaſions offred, then Satan layeth in hard. And ſo is it in other ſinnes. What ſhould I enter into particulars, ſeeing hee hath a thouſand wayes, a thouſand occaſions, yea ten thouſande ſleightes and crafty meanes for to winde in himſelfe. Alas what ſhall we doe? Our Sauiour ſaith, Watch and pray leaſt ye enter into temptation. Mat, 26. verſ. 41. And as hee ſaide to Peter, <hi>Simon, Simon, behold, Satan hath deſired to ſift you as wheat,</hi> Luk. 22.31. ſo let vs al be aſſured, that he hath many wayes to ſift vs, and to make triall what is in vs. We are taught to pray, <hi>Lead vs not into temptation:</hi> and this place doth ſhew how neceſſarie a prayer it is: for if the Lord giue ſcope to this enemie and leaue vs to our ſelues, hee will find a thouſand meanes vtterly to ſpoyle vs: hee wil euen deuour vs as his praie, and wee ſhall not perceiue it, for therein lieth the greateſt daunger, that he blindeth the eies of the minde, and harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the heart, when men feele not his working, nor imagine any ſuch thing. Hee that is ſober and doth watch, feeleth when he ſetteth vpon him, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12478:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>what harme he doth vnto him: where as on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, he may doe what he will vnto thoſe that are drunken and aſleep, and they know it not. Thus much touching the ſecond part: now let vs come to the third and laſt part.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whom reſist ſtedfaſt in the faith.</hi> If a mans ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie be too ſtrong for him by many degrees, what is he the better that he watcheth, if hee can not auoide but that he will find him &amp; come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him? will be not kill him for all his watching? The like obiection may heere be made, namely, that the power of Diuels far exceedeth all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of man: as we ſee they be deſcribed to be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and terrible: and there is no way for a man to hide himſelfe from them, but they finde him out, and come vpon him: what is hee then the better that he doth watch? Saint Peter doth anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this: that although in our own ſtrength we are nothing to this mightie roaring. Lyon yet there is a power in which we ſhall reſiſt him, put him to flight, and ouercome him, and be armed againſt al harmes: and that is the power of faith: <hi>Whome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſtedfaſt in the faith.</hi> Let it not ſeeme ſtrange vnto any, that this power ſhould reſiſt him, and keep vs in ſafetie, for it is the power of God. The Diuell is ſtrong and mightie, but what is he vnto God? God is aboue all his power is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, there is no power that can ſtand againſt it. He that is ſtedfaſt in the faith, hee is armed and ſtandeth in the power of God: for faith apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the power of God and armeth vs with it. He
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12478:13"/>that ſtandeth in the faith, ſtandeth as it were in God, compaſſed about and couered with his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. And as it is vnpoſſible that Sathan ſhoulde preuaile againſt the power of God, ſo is it vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that he ſhould ouerthrowe that man which ſtandeth ſtedfaſt in the faith: for ſo long as God cannot be ouercome, faith cannot be ouercome. Is not heere a moſt ſingular comfort and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto vs in this battaile? Let the Diuell be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo mightie, neuer ſo ſubtill, fierce and raging, we haue a rock of defence, a ſafe tower to fly vnto eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inuincible power of almighty God, which we ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d armed withal throgh faith. This is it which S. Paule teacheth where he ſpeaketh of the battell which we haue with the diuel: <hi>My brethren</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>be ſtrong in the Lord, and in his mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Put on the whole armour of God, that you may ſtand against the aſſaults of the Diuel. For we wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle not againſt bloud and fleſh, but againſt rulers, againſt powers, &amp;c. Therefore take vnto you the whole armour of God, that yee may bee able to reſiſt in the euill day, &amp; hauing finiſhed all things, ſtand. Epheſ.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.11.12.13. Now it is faith that putteth vpon vs the whole armour of God, and maketh vs ſtrong in his mighty power. It is faith, as he ſheweth in the ſame place, by which we ſhal quench all the fiery dartes of the diuell. Likewiſe S. Iohn ſetteth foorth this matter, ſaying, <hi>Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is borne of God ouercommeth the world &amp; this is the victorie that ouercommeth the worlde, euen our faith. Who is it that ouercommeth the worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:12478:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>but he that beleeueth that Ieſus is the ſon of God?</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 4.5.6. By the world he meaneth the whole corruption of ſin, or whatſoeuer is againſt the commandementes of God, and ſo the Diuell the Prince of the world is included. He that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the world, ouercommeth the prince of the world: for all the power of Satans kingdome is in darkneſſe and in ſin. Then when Saint Iohn ſaith that faith is our victorie, and that by it we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome the world, he teacheth that it is ſaith by which wee are armed with the power of God, in which we ſtand ſafe, and ouercome the Diuell.</p>
               <p>Heerby it is manifeſt what a woonderfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious thing faith is. There is no force that can ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it, he that hath obtained it cannot be poore, he cannot be vnhappy or wretched: all the diuels in hel cannot preuail againſt him. <hi>They that truſt in the Lord are as mount the Sion, which cannot be mooued, but ſtandeth faſt for euer.</hi> Pſalm. 125. verſ. 1 If it be then the moſt excellent thing that is, to ſtand ſtedfaſt in the faith: then are we aboue all other things to ſeeke after it For wiſdome tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to ſeeke moſt for the beſt thinges. Golde, pearle, and precious ſtones doe excell in price, and therefore they be greatly ſought after: and men do much reioice when they finde them. They bee more then droſſe being compared with faith, by which we put diuels to flight, and obtaine eternall glory. Shall wee not then ſeeke for faith? Shall we not make account that if we find it we haue found all? for what can a man haue more then God? And
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12478:14"/>if we miſſe of it we haue loſt all: ſeeing without it nothing can defende vs from the aſſaultes of the Diuell.</p>
               <p>But when we are willed to reſiſt the Diuel ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the faith, is it ſo that wee haue faith in our owne power, or when wee will? Can wee of our ſelues be ſtedfaſt in faith? Or is it a matter ſo eaſie to obtaine a ſtrong faith? Saint Peter hath no ſuch meaning. For goodly thinges are hard to be attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto: and faith is the moſt precious and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent of all other, &amp; moſt hard to be come by. It is not in mans will or power to beleeue and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue ſtedfaſtlie at his pleaſure. But Saint Peters meaning is, to mooue all men to ſeeke it where it is to be found, and by ſuch meanes as be orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for to come vnto it by. For there is no man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt but will acknowledge that a ſtrong faith is a moſt rich iewell: but when it commeth to the matter they depriue themſelues for the moſt part, either deeming that they haue it or can haue it in their owne power reſting in a vaine ſhadowe, not knowing at all the nature of the true, liuely, and powerfull faith: or if they doe acknowledge it to be the gift of God; yet they neuer ſeeke it by thoſe meanes which he hath ordained to worke it in men, and to nouriſh it vp in them. When wee are therefore willed to reſiſt the Diuell ſtedfaſt in the faith, it is as much as to ſaye, giue all diligence, and vſe all the wayes and meanes that may be to increaſe and ſtrengthen your faith, that you may ouercome the Diuell. If you be diligent that way,
<pb facs="tcp:12478:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>happie are you, and if you take not that courſe, then are you vtterly vndone: for what way can you then eſcape the power and tyranny of the roaring Lyon?</p>
               <p>But it will be ſaid, S. Peter doth not heere ſhewe how men ſhall come to this ſtedfaſt faith. No, for his whole doctrine tendeth to that point, in al this Epiſtle, and therefore hee needed not to put them in mind particularlie: yet it ſhall not be amiſſe for me to note ſomewhat.</p>
               <p>He that will attaine to the true, liuelie, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith, which armeth a man with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, muſt firſt of all know for certainty, that he hath not ſo much as anie ſpark thereof of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: we are all of vs by nature ſhut vp vnder vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe, and in miſerable blindneſſe: which while many doe not know they reſt and content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in a certaine dead image of faith, and are vtterlie ſeduced, for that faith hath no power. He that knoweth this indeed, beholding the depth of the calamities which hee is in, will looke vp to God who is the giuer of faith. Hee is deſirous to know what the promiſes of God are which hee is to beleeue, and what the way is in which hee muſt walke to performe the duties of a Chriſtian life: for the true faith worketh by charitie (as Paule ſaith) and cannot be without good workes. He ſearcheth the Scriptures (as Chriſt willeth, Ioh. 5.) hee doth with all diligence bende his eare to heare the holy Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt preached, feeling therein the power of God to worke faith.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12478:15"/>He doth crie and cal vnto God day &amp; night for to teach him, to lighten him, to giue him vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; to increaſe his faith: He findeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſing of God in theſe meanes, &amp; therfore applieth them. But now on the contrary part, hee that reſteth in this, God giueth faith, and if it be his will. I ſhall haue it, and ſo deſpiſeth all meanes, not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how God giueth faith, is vtterlie awrie, and out of the right way. From hence it is that there be ſo manie commendations of the word of God, and of the liuelie power that it hath to ſaue our ſoules. From hence it is that wee are often called vpon to giue eare to the voice of God, to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to his counſels.</p>
               <p>Thus ſhall wee obtaine the holy faith. And he that hath faith, and feeleth the power of God in him, if he will haue it increaſe, is to conſider the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant kindnes of God who hath beſtowed ſo great a gift vpon him, he is from the bottom of his heart to giue all praiſe and thankes and honor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for ſo great kindneſſe and mercie ſhewed. Moreouer, he is to take heed that wil be ſtedfaſt in the faith to reſiſt the diuel, that he bee rich in good workes, and that hee abſtaine from committing thoſe vices which nature doth lead vnto. For in the time of triall, in the hower of temptation, or when Satan doth aſſault, it will greatly ſhake the mind, if a man when he doth looke for the arguments of a true faith, and findeth that hee hath beene fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: but if his conſcience doe accuſe him not only of a ſlackneſſe in good workes, but alſo of foule
<pb facs="tcp:12478:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſinnes commited, then will he crie out that all his former profeſſion of the faith was but in ſhew or in hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>This Apoſtle in the firſt chapter of his ſeconde Epiſtle teacheth, that if we ioyne vertue with our faith, and with vertue knowledge, and with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge temperance, &amp; with temperance patience, and with patience godlineſſe, and with godlineſſe brotherlie kindnes, and with brotherlie kindneſſe loue: we ſhal make our calling and election ſure, we ſhall if we doe theſe thinges (as he ſaith) neuer fall. 2. Pet. 1. verſ. 5.6.10. We ſhall perceiue aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly if theſe things be in vs, that God hath called vs effectually, and that hee hath choſen vs. And therein doth conſiſt the ſtedfaſtnes of faith, euen when we are ſure that God hath choſen vs in his ſonne vnto life eternall. If this aſſurance of Gods loue and fauour towards vs were not to be attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, how could he ſay, <hi>Whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith?</hi> Can there be any ſtedfaſt faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that? I beſeech yee let vs thinke well of theſe things: let vs vſe all care and diligence, yea all the holy meanes that God hath appointed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our faith, that being armed therby, we may reſiſt and ouercome our enemie the diuell.</p>
               <p>But here it may be demaunded, whether the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell be to be reſiſted only by faith, or ſome other things to be vſed? I anſwere, that Saint Peter doth ſet downe the only way by which we are to reſiſt the diuell: we haue nothing whereby to withſtand him but faith: and that is ſufficient alone to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12478:16"/>him, whatſoeuer way hee ſekeeth to hurt vs. I ſuppoſe that the reaſon heerof is euident vnto all men. The power of God alone is ſufficient (euery man will confeſſe) to ſhielde vs from the Diuell, and no power indeed but the power of God. Faith onely armeth vs with that power of God, and maketh it as it were ours. He that ſtandeth and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth (as the the Scripture ſpeaketh) by faith, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and liueth not in himſelfe, but in the power of God. If we thinke it lawfull to ſeeke help to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him, and to put him to flight any where but in God, then may we vſe ſome other way to reſiſt him beſides faith. We are to reſiſt him by praier, will ſome ſay. That is true, for prayer is a ſpeciall fruite of faith: the liuely faith doth bring foorth true prayer. And if the prayer bee not of faith, it cannot help to deliuer vs from the tyranny of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. Faith ſendeth vp praier, yea with faſting ſtrong praier, which draweth downe the power of God vpon vs, which ſhieldeth and defendeth vs from the rage of the fiende. All other meanes that haue beene deuiſed to put diuels to flight, are vaine and friuolous, yea meere illuſions of Satans owne deuiſing, which wickedlie deface the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God. For when men cannot reſiſt by faith, then doe they flie vnto thoſe other meanes as more ſure. Wofull is the ſtate of the world in this thing: that when men wil not learne of God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the diuell: they learne at the diuell himſelfe. But that this thing may be more euident, we are to ſee how many wayes the diuell ſeeketh to deuour vs.
<pb facs="tcp:12478:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>I doe not meane that we ſhould in particulars ſee thoſe wayes by which the Diuell deuoureth the ſoules of men: for who is able ſo to expreſſe them? ſurely not any mortall man. For he hath manifold ſleightes, ſubtilties and craftes: yea euen ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand deuiſes of all ſorts to ſnare, and to entrap the ſoules withall: Hee hath alſo his forces and fierie dartes of terrour to wounde withall. It is no dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in particulars: but to bee armed ſtronglie to reſiſt him howſoeuer he commeth. My purpoſe therefore is but to touch certaine generall heads which containe the reſt. So that this cruell aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, this roaring Lyon the Diuell may catch the praie &amp; deuour it, he careth not which way it bee, for that is the ende of all, if hee may carie ſoules to hell. And therefore according to the ſeuerall ſtates and conditions that men bee in, hee frameth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſet vpon them.</p>
               <p>There is no man (I ſuppoſe) which will make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doubt that the diuel coueteth to plunge al men as deep as he can into all euill: but according as men are apt and incliued, he is faine to deale as he may, with ſome one way, with ſome another. Such as be ignorant, &amp; in darkneſſe, with them he dealeth that he may keep the pure, cleere and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie light of the Goſpell out of their harts, &amp; ſo holde them ſtill vnder the power and in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe. Touching theſe Saint Paule ſaith, <hi>If our Goſpell be hid, it is hid to thoſe that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: in whom the God of this world hath blinded the mindes euen of the infidels, leaſt the light of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12478:17"/>Goſpell of the glorie of Chriſt, ſhoulde ſhine vnto them: which is the image of God.</hi> 2. Cor. 4. verſ. 3.4. To bring this to paſſe this enemie vſeth ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all meanes, by which he may diffame the Goſpel and the profeſſion of it, as a doctrine not to bee ſuffered, breeding and drawing with it ſo manie enils As namelie, he ſoweth errours, hereſies, and wicked opinions. He is the father of al ſuch things. He raiſeth vp the heretickes and Schiſmatickes, and then ſuggeſteth to the heartes of men, which be his chiefe ſeruants, that the Goſpell hath bred them, and they proclaime it with open mouth. Behold and ſee (ſay they) what a doctrine is this, yea this new learning, that hath brought foorth ſo many foule hereſies and diuiſions. The diuell (ſay they) the diuell goeth with it. How can it be of God? how can it bee good doctrine which brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth foorth ſuch fruit?</p>
               <p>Satan did practiſe this while the holie Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were aliue vpon the earth: as we read how the falſe Apoſtles did ſeeke almoſt euerie where to pul down that which S Paule had built. S. Iohn in the Reuelation mentioneth the Nicholaitanes, and a woman which ſaid ſhe was a Propheteſſe, that taught &amp; ſeduced the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Lord, that they might commit fornication, and eat of things offred vnto Idols. And the ſame Apoſtle ſaith that in his time there were many Antichriſts (for ſo he calleth the heretikes which then were) 1. Ioh. 2. S. Paule ſaid to the Elders of Epheſus. <hi>I knowe this that after my departure there ſhall enter in among
<pb facs="tcp:12478:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>you grieuous Wolues, not ſparing the flocke, and there ſhall riſe vp of your ſelues that ſhal ſpeak per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe things to draw Diſciples after them.</hi> Act. 20. When all the Apoſtles were taken out of this life, then was this prophecie fully accompliſhed, for then did the diuell ſend foorth euen routs of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked heretickes which did ſeduce manie, &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie trouble all Churches. Then had hee thoſe which cried out: Beholde what a Goſpell is this which hath brought foorth ſo foule and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous opinions? Thus cunning lie did Satan work to keepe manie ſtill in their former blindnes. And in like maner in theſe dayes, when the light of the goſpell againe brake foorth, he raiſed vp hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible hereſies and ſectes, and then ſetteth his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants a worke to crie out: See what fruits this new Goſpell bringeth forth? This hath made many ſo much offended at it, that they will not heare it: and ſo the Diuell holdeth them ſtill in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer blindneſſe, and deuoureth them as a praie. Alſo hee raiſeth vp lies and ſlaunders to diffame both the doctrine and al that profeſſe it. This hath beene his ancient practiſe: Chriſt was ſaid to haue a diuell, to be a raiſer of ſedition, and an enemie to Ceſar. His Apoſtles were deemed to be raiſers of faction and diſturbers of the common peace, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the ſtate of princes, and the Chriſtians euer were accuſed to be men which ſecretly amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g themſelues did commit moſt foule and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinnes. True it is, that in all times he had manie which were hypocrites that profeſſed the trueth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12478:18"/>for a time and then falling into notorious offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, all the profeſſors were ſaid to be ſuch. Thus hath he in all times held many in darkneſſe, by making them out of loue with the doctrine of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. And as when Chriſt was riſen from the dead, Satan did raiſe and ſpread a lie, namely that while the watchmen were aſleep, the diſciples of Chriſt did ſteale him away, and then ſayd he was riſen, and this lie was beleeued (though it were moſt abſurd &amp; had no ſhew of liklihood) ſo looke what lies and ſlaunders he raiſeth vp nowe, manie doe beleeue them. For as S. Paul ſaith 2. Theſſ. 2. <hi>Becauſe men receiue not the loue of the truth, God ſendeth them ſtrong deluſion to beleeue lies.</hi> Nowe for a man to reſiſt the diuell in theſe practiſes, that he be not ſeduced and held in blindnes, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to haue knowledge of the trueth and a liuely ſaith. For if he come once to that, he ſhal find that the Goſpel is the pure and heauenly light, euen the power of God to ſaluation as S. Paule ſaith, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that beleeueth. Rom. 1. And that theſe ſectes and hereſies and troubles that follow it, are raiſed vp by the diuell himſelfe, euen of purpoſe to diffame the truth, that ſo men may abhorre to hear it preached. Such as haue receiued the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth and are lightened, in them hee ſeeketh how he may quench the light, or take the power of it out of their harts, and ſo deuoure them as his praie.</p>
               <p>He hath diuers wayes and means to effect this. To ſuch as be the weaker in knowledge, euen as
<pb facs="tcp:12478:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>babes in vnderſtanding of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly myſteries, he layeth ſtumbling blockes and offences, that he may cauſe them to ſtumble and fall, or to turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide out of the way into which they haue entred. He raiſeth vp terrours, troubles, and perilles to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſh them. He tempteth and leadeth into diſpair, ſhooting his fierie dartes. To auoyde theſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, there is no way, but that as S. Paule prayeth for the faithfull at Coloſſa, that we bee filled with the knowledge of the will of God in all wiſdome and ſpirituall vnderſtanding: that we may walke worthie of the Lord in all pleaſing being fruitfull in all good workes, and increaſing in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God: ſtrengthened in all might through his glorious power, vnto all patience and long ſuffering with ioyfulneſſe, Coloſſ. 1. verſ. 9.10.11. Some others that haue receiued more knowledge he ſeeketh to caſt downe through pride and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, he tempteth them to be puffed vp, and to ſwell, and ſo leadeth them into ſectes, errours, and hereſies, as his fit occaſion ſerueth, one parte into one, another into another.</p>
               <p>Heere is need of ſound knowledge of heauenlie thinges, and of that ſincere faith which purgeth the heart, and emptieth it of pride and humaine preſumption, leading men to reſt only vpon God with feare and trembling, euen with true humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Alſo as hee perceiueth mens inclination, hee tempteth and leadeth them into grieuous and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable ſinnes, and ſuch as God is highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed withal, ſome into one, and ſome into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12478:19"/>and ſo caſteth them downe. And in this hee is woonderfull ſubtill, and can finde what ſinne a man may moſt eaſilie bee brought into. If he bee inclined to vaine mirth and leſting, hee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to fit him with companions for that: that when he hath receiued the touch of heauenlie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that vaine mirth may put it out. If hee bee inclined to vncleane luſtes of fornication, he wil finde the meanes (if it bee poſſible) to ſet as it were the bait before him, where hee may bee inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And ſo is it in all other vices: ſo that men had need watch and pray leaſt they enter into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. They neede to bee armed with a ſtedfaſt faith to renſte, that by their faith, all the firie dartes of this horrible enemie may bee quenched. His ſubtilties to keepe men in blindneſſe, his lies and ſlaunders to driue men from the Goſpell, his aſſaultes to lead into deſpaire, his ſtumbling blocks and terrours to turne men out of the way, his temptation to leade into hereſies and ſectes, or into any foule ſinne, or whatſoeuer dartes hee ſhooteth, there is no way to reſiſt him, and to be kept ſafe, but by a true, a liuely, and a ſtedfaſt faith. Therefore (beloued) ſeeing this enemie is ſo vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, &amp; doth ſo cruellie ſeek our deſtruction night and day, euen to ſwallow vs vp into the gulfe of hell: and ſeeing he hath ſo manie ſleightes, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny trappes, ſo manie baytes and allurementtes, ſo manie firy dartes to wounde vnto death: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are ſo readie to bee ſeduced, hauing no power of our ſelues; let vs ſeeke to bee ſtronglie
<pb facs="tcp:12478:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>armed with the power of God, that ſo wee may get the victorie. There is no way for vs to bee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the power of God, but by faith; ſo that the ende of all is this, that men labour for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and ſtrengthening of their faith: vſe all good meanes and that continually for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the ſame. If vpon ſuch a danger wee will not bee admoniſhed by this wholeſome admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtle, we are more then fooliſh or mad.</p>
               <p>It may be ſome man will ſay that the diuell is to be reſiſted onlie by faith when he commeth to hurte the ſoule: but is it not another caſe when he commeth to hurte the bodie, the cattell, or the goods of a man? Is he then alſo to be reſiſted on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by faith? Or is it all one when he commeth to doe thoſe thinges of himſelfe, and when he is ſent to doe them by witches and ſorcerers? Is there now no meanes to reſiſt him but by faith? To an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to this queſtion, firſt it is to bee graunted that the diuels doe indeed delight to torment and to hurt man any way. And withal we ſee it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie taught in the ſcriptures that he hath had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and leaue ſometimes graunted vnto him ſo for to hurt: As it was granted vnto him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Iobs goods, ſome by fire, and ſome taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by robbers: to kill his children, and then to plague him in his body with moſt grieuous ſores. Wee read of many in the Goſpell whoſe bodies were poſſeſſed with diuelles, and whome hee did torment in verie grieuous maner.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:12478:20"/>
               <p> And we muſt know withall that when he doth hurt in the bodie or in the goods, his chiefe drift and practiſe is thereby to deſtroy both body and ſoule, and ſo he may make it a meane to win the ſoule, hee will ceaſe for to hurt the body, ſeeming as if he were expelled. We read in the Goſpell of two poſſeſſed with diuels, and Ieſus caſting forth the Diuels, they beſought him to giue them leaue to enter into an hearde of ſwine, hee gaue them leaue, they entered, and caried the whole learde of ſwine headlong from a ſteepe place into the ſea, and drowned them, Math. 8. What was the purpoſe of thoſe Diuelles, what was their deſire? Was it no more then for to deſtroy the poore dumbe beaſtes? Yes verely they had a further reach, &amp; a deeper practiſe. This it was, they ſought to bring Chriſt into hatred with the men of that region among whom hee was nowe come: and why? but euen that they might not heare him bringing the word of life. They knewe that thoſe men were worldly minded, and that the loſſe of their hogges woulde grieue them ſore, and that they had rather be without Chriſt, then that hee ſhould bring them ſuch loſſe. And ſo it came to paſſe, for the men of that citie came forth and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him to depart out of their coaſtes. Here was a craftie conueyance, and ſo Satan, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he obtayneth power to hurt the body of man, his cattell or goods, it is not without ſome great ſubtiltie of a further and a greater miſchiefe which he ſeeketh to worke. Then further we may
<pb facs="tcp:12478:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>bee ſure that it is all one whether he come of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or be ſent by a witch. For I take it, none will be ſo ſimple as to imagine that if hee haue power to hurt, that he will lie ſtill and not hurt vnleſſe hee be ſent by ſome man or woman. And if hee haue not leaue granted him from God, no mortal crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can giue him power to touch the body or cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of a man. Howſoeuer he commeth, wee muſt knowe it is the Lorde GOD of heauen that hath ſent him, euen as hee gaue him leaue to deale with Iob.</p>
               <p>Then it muſt needs follow, that there is no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer for to reſiſt him withall, but the power of God: and there is no way to be armed with that power, but onelie by faith. If there bee no way to withſtand Satan but by the power of God (as it is moſt wicked to denie) and through faith onelie man is armed with that power, what other way or meanes can there bee to reſiſt him? There was a child poſſeſſed with a Diuell: the father brought him to the Diſciples of Chriſt, that they might caſt him out; but they could not: Ieſus caſt him out. Then the Diſciples did aske him why they coulde not caſt him out? Hee ſaid vnto them, becauſe of your vnbeleefe. This kind (ſaith he) goeth not out but by prayer &amp; faſting, Math. 17. Where wee ſee that the diuel torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting the body, is to be caſt out by faith, yea by a ſtrong faith, which is to bee aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with faſting and prayer. But what if the diuell (ſay ſome) afflicting the bodie, or deſtroying the goods cannot be remooued by faith or withſtood,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12478:21"/>ſhall not men then ſeeke to remooue him, or to withſtande him ſome other wayes? As wee are taught by experience, that the diuell poſſeſſing the bodie of ſome man, woman or child, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the ſame, prayer hath been vſed, and that very often, and yet no remedie hath beene found, but by other meanes he hath been expelled. Yea, ſome haue been of that minde that God hauing giuen Satan power to touch their bodies, their children, or their goods, they would ſeeke no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but to God, ſaying, that as hee had giuen him power, ſo when it ſhould pleaſe him hee woulde reſtraine him, and thereupon they would reſt: but in the ende they haue beene glad to vſe other meanes. God hath appointed meanes, and they tempt God that refuſe them. If a man be fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ditch, and lie ſtill praying, God helpe mee, Lord help me, and doth not ſtir to clime out, hee may he long enough. If there be meanes by which the diuell is driuen out, why ſhould not men vſe them, ſeeing we may ſuppoſe that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed thoſe meanes? To anſwere vnto theſe thinges, we may firſt conſider, that the Lord God for the triall of their faith and patience, doth giue leaue to Satan to afflict his children. This is for their good. What ſhould I vſe any proofe for this, but the exemple of Iob? He was throughlie tried. Now ſeeing it was the will of God that he ſhould ſo be tried, both for his owne good, and for the inſtruction of many others, though his faith were a right ſtrong faith, yet in this thing it did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb facs="tcp:12478:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Satan, but he had power giuen him to touch his goods, children and body. And ſo we may hold it vndoubtedly, that if God will giue power or leaue vnto Satan to touch the bodie, the children, or the goods of any faithfull man, for ſuch a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as this was in Iob, faith doth not remooue him from ſo afflicting: but faith in thoſe ſo for a time afflicted doth reſiſt him, ſo that hee doth not nor cannot preuaile againſt the ſoule. That is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for vs. Such a man is to ſubmit himſelfe to the chaſtiſement of God for his trial. If Satan can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be remooued from hurting him in thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thinges which are of leſſe value, let him hold faſt that he reſiſt him by faith, ſo that hee win not his ſoule and he is well: the Lord God will in his good time deliuer him from that other calamitie. Let him knowe it is for his good that he is ſo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed.</p>
               <p>The woman of Canaan, Math. 15. was a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of a wonderfull faith, for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I haue not found ſo great faith in Iſraell,</hi> and yet the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell did torment her daughter. She did not ſeeke any other meanes, but ſought out Chriſt, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of him to haue the Diuell caſt out, which did ſo grieuouſly torment her child. This was for her triall, and ſhe did for the time endure it reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the diuell ſo mightilie by faith that he could not preuaile againſt her ſoule.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the diuell hath power giuen vnto him to afflict ſome, and to plague them in their bodies or in their goods, becauſe of their ſinnes.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12478:22"/>They haue deſpiſed the lawes of God, they bee careleſſe to knowe the way of ſaluation. When this ſcourge is vpon them, they are to weigh and to conſider how grieuouſlie they haue offended, and how much they haue prouoked the Lorde to wrath, who hath therfore giuen leaue to this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enemie ſo to plague them. They ſhould nowe ſeeke vnto the Lorde and intreate him to haue mercie vpon them. They ſhould lament and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile their ſinnes, and turne from their wicked wayes vnto the way of righteouſneſſe: and then ſhould this their calamitie be a meane to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neerer to God, to the ſaluation of their ſoules. They are to intreat the Lorde vpon their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to remooue the plague from them. And if it bee not remooued, they are ſtill more and more to be humbled, they ought to faſt and pray, yea they are to vſe all good meanes to come to the true knowledge of God, and to a ſound faith, that they may eſcape from being deuoured by this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie vnto eternall damnation. If the Lorde doe not deliuer them by and by, but that they be tormented in their owne bodies, or in their children or goods, let them knowe it is becauſe they doe not ſo throughly repent, nor ſo through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſeek the Lord as they ought to doe. Let them therefore yet humble themſelues further, and ſeek more earneſtlie to knowe the way of God, and to be armed with true and liuely faith.</p>
               <p>There was a woman which had a ſpirite of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie eighteen yeares, and was bowed together
<pb facs="tcp:12478:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>and was bowed together, and could in no wiſe lift vp her ſelfe: Ieſus healed her, and ſaid, that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan had bound her eighteen yeares. Luk. 13. ver. 11.13.15. If the Lord ſhall giue Satan power ſo long to afflict, let vs not fall from God: let vs not ſeek to reſiſt him anie way but by faith. Ye ſay it is knowne by experience, that where the diuell hath tormented ſome, prayer and all holie means haue beene vſed, and yet no helpe at all, vntill other meanes haue been ſought. Then belike there be meanes which are ſtronger againſt the deuill then faith &amp; prayer. And there is ſome power mightier againſt him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power of god: for thoſe means which ſome men flie vnto, when as they cannot preuaile by faith, are ſuch as they which are afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted haue learned either by a preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel himſelf, ſaying, let ſuch or ſuch a thing be don, and there ſhall be remedie; or els they haue them preſcribed by ſome wiſe man, or wiſe woman, who haue them from the diuell. Theſe be very pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie things (as there be a number, I need not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate them, they bee too well knowne, and too much practiſed) and yet they be more ſought vnto then faith is, which armeth vs with the power of God. What a diſhonor is this to the high Maieſtie of the Almightie? What an infidelitie is it? Shall men run to the diuell for help? Is he fitter to teach them or of more power then God?</p>
               <p>But ye ſay, we ſee the thing is wrought by thoſe meanes which could not otherwiſe be obtayned, Satan is expelled, and eaſe hath followed. Hath Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12478:23"/>expelled Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? or hath he taught how he might be expelled indeede? Is the diuell become ſo ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Wil he hinder his owne kingdome? Are men ſo fooliſh as to beleeue that he is by ſuch things in very deed driuen out? A man tormented ſore in his bodie, he feareth that it is ſome witch that hath done it. He is aduiſed by his neighbours to ſende vnto ſome cunning man. Worde is ſent backe, that indeed he hath bad neighbours: let him do ſuch or ſuch a thing, and he ſhal haue eaſe. Well, he doth it &amp; hath eaſe. What ſhall we think that the diuell is driuen out? A wofull driuing out. He doth ceaſe from tormenting the bodie for a time, that he may enter deeper into the ſoule. He winneth by this driuing out. The like may be ſaid where he hath power giuen vnto him to deſtroy mens cattell. They be taught many thinges howe to reſiſt him: among other to offer ſome burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering vnto him, they muſt burne ſomwhat aliue. Well he commeth no more: there is a power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue faith that hath put him to flight. And where as you ſay that ſome haue beene of the minde that they would not ſeek any way or meanes, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God, and would reſt vntil he ſhould reſtrain the diuell: but haue been glad in the ende to vſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes. It is a lamentable hearing, that the faith of any ſhould ſo far faile: that in ſteed of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching neerer to God by ſtrong repentance, they haue turned to the counſell of the diuell. If they could not find helpe by praier, they might be aſſured that the Lord would yet afflict them fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:12478:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; that with al humblenes they ought to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues vnder his mightie hand: yea they ought to haue conſidered the weakneſſe of their faith, and the grieuouſnes of their ſinnes, and ſo haue ſought by all meanes poſſible to get a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt faith, and vnfained repentance. This their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by Satan ſhould haue been a warning vnto them, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cleaue more firmlie to God, &amp; to look better to themſelues, and ſee how it hath driuen them to run backe from God to the diuell. But you ſay God hath appointed meanes, and hee that refuſeth the meanes tempteth God. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſhal a man crie, Lord help, and not ſtirre? Indeed if you could prooue that God had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch meanes to driue away diuels where faith cannot, your ſaying were true. But where can you prooue in al the whole word of God that any ſuch meanes are appointed to put diuels to flight? If thoſe meanes be not in the holie Scriptures, they be not ordained of God, they be not of faith, it is not the power of God that expelleth Satan, but it is his owne ſleight that ſeemeth to be repelled and vanquiſhed, when he is not; they be means of his own deuiſing, which he hath taught by thoſe that haue familiarity with him.</p>
               <p>The holie Scriptures do condemne it as a moſt wicked thing, that men ſhould haue any dealing with diuels to be taught at their handes. Wee are to be taught of God, Chriſt Ieſus is our onely Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor: ſhall we then learne at the mouth of Diuels? A man is taken lame, he ſuſpecteth that hee is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12478:24"/>he ſendeth to the cunning man: Hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth whom they ſuſpect, and then ſheweth the image of the partie in a glaſſe. When this is done he ſheweth and preſcribeth what the lame man ſhall doe for to get remedie: howe hee ſhall cauſe the olde witch to come vnto him, and how he ſhall vſe her. Heer all is done by the direction of the diuell: are theſe meanes then appointed by God? Alſo there is one whome Sathan doth as it were poſſeſſe and doth torment the bodie: there is ſeeking vnto god, but not like the Cananitiſh wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man that came to Chriſt to haue the diuel driuen out of her daughter, who with the ſtrength of her faith would not be denied, Math. 15. but like to king Saule, who receiuing no anſwere from God, gate him by and by vnto a Witch: for not finding helpe by faith and prayer, or by thoſe waies that God hath appointed, they then begin to hearken to the diuell, and he telleth them that if they ſhall doe ſuch a thing, ſuch a diuell ſhall depart. Heere be the meanes, which ſome doe holde to bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God.</p>
               <p>But is not this a woonderfull blindnes that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan can ſet vp himſelfe to bee a teacher, and men learning of him, ſhall thinke that they learne of God? Well ſay ſome, wee are glad to haue eaſe, we find that the diuell is expelled, we may think that God doth allow it. Shall a man be glad for to buy eaſe ſo deare? May we call that eaſe, when the diuell ceaſeth to vexe the body for a time, to the end that he may torment ſoule and bodie in hell
<pb facs="tcp:12478:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>for euer? If a man be ſicke of a burning ague, and take that to coole the heat and to giue eaſe for the time, which will afterwarde cauſe it to bee more burning, is that a good remedie? Is that a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, which for a little while doth ſeeme to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate, but afterward doth increaſe the diſeaſe? E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo the blind people doe imagine that Satan is expelled by thoſe meanes, by which indeed he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth more deepe into them. For tell me but this, wherein doth the kingdome of the Diuel conſiſt? Is he not called the prince of this world, and the prince of darkneſſe? This his kingdome doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in infidelitie, in darkneſſe and in ſinne. Hee that is vnder the power of ſinne, ſo that ſinne hath dominion ouer him, hee is vnder the power and working of Satan. Sinne is his kingdome, there is his throne, ye cannot ſeparate them, he cannot be caſt forth, and ſinne ſtill remaine in force. If pride, enuie, couetouſneſſe, hatred, malice, ſelfe-loue, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, or any other ſuch ſinne doe raigne and rule in the heart of man, there ruleth the diuell: for theſe be the workes of the diuell. Heereupon our Sauiour ſaid to the Iewes, <hi>Ye are of your father the diuell: ye doe the workes of your father. Ioh.</hi> 8. Hee that will then caſte foorth the diuell, hee muſt caſt out thoſe workes. For hee that committeth ſinne is of the diuell, as Saint Iohn ſaith in his firſt Epiſtle chap. 3. Hee that ſtill committeth ſinne, and therefore is of the diuell, is the diuell expelled or driuen from him? I ſuppoſe that there is no man ſo void of reaſon, that he will imagine, that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12478:25"/>the diuell is driuen away from that man in whoſe heart he hath his throne and power. A man is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the word and waies of God: with his ignorance of neceſſitie goeth vnbeleefe: with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe there goe the vnfruitfull workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. There is much vanitie of minde, there is much prophaneneſſe, there be foule errors and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable vices.</p>
               <p>This man hath ſome of his cattell deſtroyed by the diuell: he would haue the diuel expelled, he hath not faith which armeth men with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God: he hath not the faith which ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the world, 1. Ioh. 5. or which purgeth the heart. Act. 15. or which quencheth all the firie dartes of the diuell. Epheſ 6. or (as Saint Peter ſaith heere) reſiſteth him: And ſeeketh ſome other helps to reſiſt him, yea, to be deliuered from him, and neuer doth conſider that hee is firſt to haue him remooued out of his heart. He ſhould conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the diuell (as Saint Paule ſaith) worketh in the children of diſobedience. Epheſ. 2. verſ. 2. And therfore ſo long as he is diſobedient to God, Satan cannot bee caſt foorth of his heart. If thoſe things can reſiſt Satan which men doe learne and practiſe heere in the world, as there be a thouſand deuiſes, by which he perſwadeth the world that he is reſiſted: then it skilleth not whether a man bee godlie or vngodlie, faithful or vnfaithful, touching the reſiſting &amp; putting diuelles to flight. If when a mans cattell are plagued and deſtroyed by the diuell, it will deliuer the reſt if he burne one aliue:
<pb facs="tcp:12478:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>this way may the Iew, or the Turke, or the heathen caſt him out as well as the Chriſtian. And ſo it may be ſaid in all other their wicked means. They tend wholie therefore to this ende, that men may be held in infidelitie, in blindneſſe, and hardneſſe of heart, euen void of repentance for their ſinnes, that is the craftineſſe of Satan. For if diuels can bee put to flight and ouercome by ſuch meanes, men will neuer ſeek to be armed with faith, they neuer care for true repentance: they bee perſwaded that the diuell hath nothing to doe with them. And therein lyeth one of the greateſt ſubtilties of Satan that hee may deuour men when they dreame of no perill, and therefore ſeek not to God, to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with his mightie power through faith. For when men doe knowe that there is no way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape but by faith (as Saint Peter ſaith heer, <hi>whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith</hi>) if they be not mad, they will haue a care to attaine to that true faith.</p>
               <p>In the Poperie there were many things deuiſed to driue away diuels. Men were perſwaded that the ſigne of the Croſſe did put him to flight. They had their coniured holiwater to ſprinkle vpon the men, and in their houſes, &amp; thither the Diuel might not come. Likewiſe if a man had a peece of holie bread in his purſe, or any where about him, hee was armed, hee might goe ſafe in the darkeſt night that was. There were hallowed candles, and within the light of them the wicked Prince of darkneſſe could not approch. But there was yet a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12478:26"/>ſtronger thing and a more terrible vnto the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, then all the reſt, euen to hunt them out of the countrie.</p>
               <p>The Lorde ſendeth lightening and thunder, and mightie windes: hee doth therby declare his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. When theſe tempeſtes doe ariſe, the diuell woulde gladly make men beleeue that hee hath raiſed them: hee would be as a God of power: and therfore he coueteth to ſhew himſelf in thoſe tempeſtes, and ſo doth come with terrour. To meet with this miſchiefe and to repell him, the Papiſtes had their hallowed belles, their Saintes belles, and thoſe they did ring out when any terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tempeſt did approch, truſting that the ſounde of them would repel him, and put him to flight. O how the Diuell was skared with theſe things! S. Peter forgate himſelfe that he did not tel of theſe, and not ſpeake of reſiſting him by nothing but by faith. Such readie helpes for to defend men, and ſo eaſie, and not one of the Apoſtles would tell of them: but ſpeake only of faith to bee our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie. Well (beloued) knowe for certaintie that all theſe are but ſleights of the Diuell: which were vſed in the poperie, and which many at this day doe vſe when they ſuppoſe that they are bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Leaue all ſuch vngodly waies which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell teacheth, and hearken to the holy Ghoſt, which willeth you to reſiſt the Diuell ſtedfaſt in the faith. Let all your ſtudie, and induſtrie, and care be, to bee armed with a ſtrong and liuelie
<pb facs="tcp:12478:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>faith. That ſhall couer you, and compaſſe you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with the almighty power of God. Yee ſhall bee as the mount Sion (ſaith the Prophete in the Pſalme) that cannot be remoued. All the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall powers (or as Chriſt ſaith, the gates of hell) ſhall not preuaile againſt it. If you haue that faith, the roaring Lyon ſhall not deuoure you: but all his firie dartes ſhall bee quenched. Hee will doe what he can to holde you in blindneſſe, to leade you into ſinne, and into hereſies, he wil tempt you to deſpaire, but your faith ſhall preuaile. He will ſeek to hurt your bodies &amp; goods, reſiſt him by faith. Bleſſed be our Lord that hath giuen vs ſuch a tower of refuge. Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:12478:27"/>
               <head>THE SECOND SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vpon 1. Peter, chap. 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>and</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Home reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith.</hi> We haue heard the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation or warning which Saint Peter giueth vnto all men to be ſober and watch. Wee haue alſo in the ſecond place ſeene the cauſe why it behooueth vs to be watchfull. There is an aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie that doth ſeek to deuoure vs both ſoules and bodies vnto eternall deſtruction. <hi>Your aduerſarie the diuell</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>like a roaring Lyon walketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, ſeeking whom hee may deuour.</hi> In the thirde place we haue been taught how to withſtand him and to get the victorie ouer him. <hi>Whom reſist ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the faith.</hi> Where it hath beene ſhewed that faith armeth a man with the power of God. The power of God is inuincible &amp; cannot be brought vnder, but getteth the victorie ouer all the terrible might of Diuels: ſo that it is not poſſible that hee ſhould be ouercome which hath faith. It conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all the infernall powers, and triumpheth at all
<pb facs="tcp:12478:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>times moſt gloriouſly ouer them. Whereby it is manifeſt what a woonderfull rich and precious iewell faith is. It preſerueth vs ſafe from diuelles, and therefore is to bee coueted and ſought for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all treaſures. It is to bee ſought for at the handes of God, he is the giuer of it, and it is not a thing which is in mans owne power. Moreouer, ſeeing God doth giue it, and nouriſh it by means, he that will be ſtedfaſt in the faith, muſt vſe thoſe meanes that be ordained. Alſo it hath beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that faith is the onlie thing by which wee are to reſiſt the Diuell: in as much as faith alone armeth vs with the glorious power of God. Satan hath manie waies whereby he ſeeketh to deuoure and to ſwallow vp into hell the ſoules and bodies of men: as to holde ſome in blindneſſe and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to lead others into ſectes, errours and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, to drawe men into vices and abominable ſinnes, to plague the bodies and the cattell of men? but which way ſoeuer hee commeth, faith doth quench all his firie dartes arming the ſoule of man, couering and compaſſing it round about with the mightie power of God. Al thoſe vain, yea thoſe moſt wicked means by which men ſeek to repell Satan, are to be renounced as meere illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Men are to bee taught of God, and not to learne of diuelles: but Diuelles haue deuiſed thoſe means, and by ſuch as haue familiaritie with them haue deliuered the ſame to bee put in practiſe. As there be ſuch deuiſes among the Sorcerers which Satan hath craftily conueighed in: ſo alſo in the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12478:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Poperie they did not ſeeke as Saint Peter willeth to reſiſt him by faith, but inuented other wayes. Thus far we proceeded in handling this Scripture: And now it remaineth as a principall queſtion to be handeled, whether this faith, by which the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell is to be reſiſted, can be ouercome in any? that is, to ſpeake more plainlie, whether any man that hath the true and liuelie faith, by which the diuell is reſiſted, can vtterly looſe it, and fall from God finallie? whether his faith may vtterly faile and be vanquiſhed, &amp; ſo hauing reſiſted Satan for a time ſtedfaſt in the faith, yet in the end he may be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and deuoured by him?</p>
               <p>Touching this queſtion, the Papiſts doe holde that a man may haue the true and liuely faith, and ſo fall from it, as that it be vtterly &amp; wholie quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in him, yea finally. And ſo by their doctrine ſuch as doe ſtand in this faith which Saint Peter requireth, and with the ſame doe reſiſt the diuel, may by the diuell haue that ſame their ſound and true faith ouercome, and ſo periſh eternally. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there be, who will ſeeme to differ ſomewhat from the Popiſh ſort about this matter, and they do hold that the verie reprobate (ſome of them at the leaſt) are partakers for a time of the true, liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and iuſtifying faith, which is afterward wholie and finallie extinguiſhed in them. Moreouer, they doe hold, that the ſame true and liuely faith may be wholy extinguiſhed in the elect, but not finally, becauſe it is vnpoſſible that the elect ſhuld periſh, and therein they differ indeede from the
<pb facs="tcp:12478:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Papiſtes, which make election conditionall. If this doctrine of theirs bee true, then is there no man that can be certaine of his ſaluation. There is no man that is ſure he ſhall ſtand to the end, no man can reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith. For hee that to day doth get the victorie ouer the diuell by a true and liuely faith, to morrow may vtterly looſe his faith, and be ouercome by the diuell. If it bee ſo, then hath not Saint Peter heer taught how we ſhal haue vndoubted victorie: if he will vs to reſiſt by ſuch a weapon as may be broken or deſtroyed, or plucked away from vs, wee are then but in a very weake caſe.</p>
               <p>It may be they will ſay, there is vndoubted vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie ſo long as a man doth reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith: and that Saint Peter hath no further intent. That is the thing which we are to enquire of. And this ſhall be made manifeſt, that whoſoeuer hath the true and liuely faith, ſhall vndoubtedly get the victorie ouer Satan: that it is vnpoſſible that his faith ſhould be wholie extinguiſhed, it is vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that he ſhould periſh.</p>
               <p>This is it which we affirme, that whoſoeuer doth attaine vnto a ſtedfaſt faith (which is the thing which Saint Peter here requireth) that faith can neuer bee ouercome: for if it bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, it is not ſtedfaſt. It is the purpoſe of Saint Peter, not to teach that ſo long as a man is ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the faith, ſo long he ſhall reſiſt the Diuell, and get the victorie, taking this, ſo long, as if it were vncertaine that hee which is once ſtedfaſt,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12478:29"/>ſhall continue to the end: but this is his full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that ſo manie as attaine to be ſtedfaſt in the faith, ſhall vndoubtedlie vanquiſh Satan, and neuer be vanquiſhed by him. Hitherto then ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his doctrine, euen to ſhewe, that as wee are compaſſed about and beſet with diuels, who like moſt greedy deuouring Lyons doe ſeeke conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually for to ſwallowe vs vp: ſo if we ſeek ſo farre as to be armed with a ſtedfaſt faith, wee attaine to that eſtate out of which wee can neuer bee caſt. It is as much as if he ſhould ſay, the Diuell can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ouercome a ſtedfaſt faith: obtaine that and you are ſure to ſtand to the end.</p>
               <p>Beloued, wee are not then to labour onelie for faith, but if we will be ſure to ouercome the diuel, and to ſtand to the end, we muſt labour to obtain a ſtedfaſt faith. But how can we bee ſure that this is the mind of the Apoſtle, to warrant men, that they ſhall get the victorie ouer the diuell, euen to the end, if they attaine vnto a ſtedfaſt faith? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that hee agreeth with himſelfe, teaching here the ſame thing which hee exhorteth vnto in the firſt chapter of his ſecond Epiſtle: <hi>Here unto</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>giue all diligence, in your faith miniſter vertue, in vertue knowledge, in knowledge tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in temperance patience, in patience godlines, in godlineſſe brotherlie kindneſſe, in brother he kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe loue. For if theſe things be among you, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, they will make that you neither ſhall be idle nor vnfruitful in the knowledging of our lord Ieſus Chriſt. For he that hath not theſe thinges is blinde,
<pb facs="tcp:12478:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>and cannot ſee a farre off, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his olde ſinnes. Wherefore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren giue rather diligence to make your calling &amp; election ſure: for if ye doe theſe thinges, ye ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fall. For by this means an entring ſhal be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto you abundantly into the euerlaſting king dome of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.6.7.8.9.10.11. In this place S. Peter doth moſt plainlie affirme that they which haue ſuch a faith as goeth with thoſe fruites, they come to an aſſurance that they be called of god, &amp; choſen vnto life and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and he doth aſſure and warrant them that they ſhall neuer fail. Hee addeth as a reaſon that they haue an entrance into the kingdome of Chriſt, which is euerlaſting. If the true liuely faith may faile and be wholy loſt, what aſſurance can anie man haue that hee is called of God and choſen to life eternall? Or how could the holie Apoſtle ſay, <hi>If yee doe theſe things ye ſhall neuer fall?</hi> Doe not they fall which looſe the faith, or in whome it is wholy quenched? Chriſt raigneth in all thoſe which haue the liuely faith, and if his kingdome may be broken downe againe where it once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth place, how can it be ſaid in euery reſpect to be eternall?</p>
               <p>Now to ioyne theſe two places together, that man hath the ſtedfaſt faith whereby he doth reſiſt the diuel, which doth thoſe things which S. Peter mentioneth, and thereby is ſure hee is called and choſen, and that he ſhall neuer fall. Hee is firme &amp; ſtedfaſt in the faith which commeth vnto this:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12478:30"/>and ſuch as haue proceeded no further in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of a fruitfull faith, but that they be ſtill vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whether they ſhall ſtand to the ende, howe can they be ſaid to reſiſt the diuell ſtedfaſt in the faith? When S. Paule telleth vs that the ſhielde of faith doth quench all the firie dartes of the Diuel, it is to giue courage and comfort, that ſuch as haue once gotten that ſhield, ſhall neuer be ouercome: for if the faith bee ouercome, then it doth not quench them all. The like courage and comfort Saint Peter doth heere miniſter, by ſhewing that being ſtedfaſt in the faith Satan is reſiſted. Where a man is ſure to get the victorie how valiantlie hee doth fight, what aſſaultes he wil endure, and with what comfort and conſolation of minde. But if the battell be made doubtfull, that although hee haue ſo liuely a faith which woorketh by charitie, yet he may looſe it, he may be ouercome, it daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and diſcourageth, it taketh away the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conſolation. And this is to ouerthrowe that which the Lord of ſpeciall purpoſe hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted to his children, namely, that in all the trials, and afflictions, and temptations which they paſſe through, they may haue ſtrong conſolation. For it is written, <hi>Wherein God willing more abundantlie to ſhewe vnto the heires of promiſe the ſtableneſſe of his counſell confirmed by an oth, that by two immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table things in which it was impoſſible for God to ly, we might haue ſtrong conſolation. Heb.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 17.18. If God hath confirmed his promiſe by an oth, that all they which beleeue in his ſonne ſhall haue
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:12478:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>eternall life, why is it, or to what end is it, but that wee ſhould come to the aſſurance of ſaluation, without which aſſurance there can be no ſtrong conſolation? If men bee condemned for high treaſon, and then ſome hope of pardon followeth, it ſomewhat comforteth that they may ſuppoſe it may be they ſhall eſcape the tormentes of death, and not be executed; but ſo long as there is doubt they haue no ſtrong conſolation: but when they know aſſuredly, &amp; haue it confirmed vnto them that they are ſet free by pardon, then is their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation ſtrong indeede. We are all of vs for high treaſon againſt God condemned to hell to endure eternall tormentes: A couenant and promiſe is made, that ſo many as doe beleeue in the ſonne of God ſhall haue free pardon, and ſo not onelie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape from thoſe endleſſe miſeries, but alſo be lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp into eternall glorie. So manie as doe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſenſiblie conſider this wofull and miſerable eſtate, in which all are in by nature, cannot but be touched with great horror and fear. For is it a light matter to be caſt with the diuell and his Angels into eternal fire? Is hee not more then mad which can be merie ſo long as he is ſubiect vnto ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible damnation? Wel, there is hope of pardon, that ſo hee ſhall eſcape, in as much as God hath not only giuen his ſonne to bee a redeemer, but hath promiſed and bounde that his promiſe with an oath, that euery one which beleeueth ſhall bee ſaued. Hee feeleth that he hath a faith, and it doth comfort him: but vntill he feele that the ſame his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12478:31"/>faith is the true and liuelie faith which getteth the victorie ouer Satan, and which can neuer be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, he cannot haue ſtrong conſolation. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall woe with the diuelles in hell is a moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous thing, &amp; vnpoſſible it is that any man ſhuld haue ſtrong conſolation, vnleſſe he be ſure that he ſhall be deliuered from it: Whereupon it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that feeing the bleſſed Lord God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that his children ſhall heere in the midſt of the battell againſt Satan haue ſtrong conſolation, that he doth alſo giue vnto them aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of faith, yea ſuch a faith as they doe knowe can neuer be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome. Take away the one &amp; take away the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Wherby we ſee that they which do hold that the true and liuelie faith may be wholy loſt, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ſtableneſſe of Gods couenant. If they will obiect that manie haue great gladneſſe and conſolation which haue not any true ſaith, I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that the blind world is drowned in a carnall conſolation, they doe not ſoundly beleeue, nor ſenſiblie conſider what eſtate they be in. They be but as drunken men, who through exceeding drunkenneſſe paſsing towards horrible torments, do not perceiue it nor regard it, but are merie and laugh and ſport themſelues: For they which are ſo merie and doe ſport themſelues ſo much in ſinne and in carnall pleaſures, if they did knowe or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly conſider whither they be going and what remaineth for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it would dampe all their mirth. It is not the ſtrong conſolation which the holie Ghoſt ſpeaketh of, that they haue. Theirs is but a
<pb facs="tcp:12478:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>drunken madneſſe. Such onlie as by a liuely faith doe feele the power of Chriſt in them mortifying and ſlaying ſinne, &amp; quickening them vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and true holineſſe euen to walke in the light, and to bring forth the fruites and vertues of the ſpirite, haue the ſtrong conſolation. They bee aſſured that they be deliuered from hell, and made heires of eternall glorie: in as much as they know that God doth ſanctifie none but thoſe whome he doth glorifie. But they doe alleage ſundrie teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the holie Scriptures, by which they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prooue that the verie reprobate haue the true, liuely and iuſtifying faith, which they do vtterlie looſe: and likwiſe, that the elect doe ſo fall, that the ſame true and liuelie faith for a time is vtterlie quenched in them. if it be ſo, then all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance is gone, and with it there vaniſheth away all ſtrong conſolation. For if the true faith bee in the reprobate, then cannot any man thus argue, I haue the true, liuely and ſanctifying faith, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am choſen of God and ſure to bee ſaued. Neither can he ſay thus, If I fall, I ſhal riſe againe: for what is it that can aſſure him that he ſhall riſe againe, if ſome that haue the ſame true faith which he hath, doe fal and neuer riſe againe? Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider what their proofes bee, or teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies vpon which they ſtande, to prooue that the true faith may be vtterly loſt. In the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is thus written, <hi>But when the righteous doth turne away from his righteouſneſſe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit iniquity, and doth according to all the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12478:32"/>which the wicked doth, ſhould he liue? all his righteous deedes which he hath done ſhall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred: for his tranſgreſſion in which hee tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth, and for his ſinne in which hee ſinneth, for theſe he ſhall die. Ezech.</hi> 18.24. The Lord Ieſus ſaith, that there bee ſome which do beleeue for a time, &amp; in time of temptation goe away. Luk. 8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Thou ſtandeſt</hi> (ſaith S. Paul) <hi>by faith: be not high minded, but feare,</hi> Rom. 11. ver. 20. Alſo the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaketh of ſome that made ſhipwrack of the faith 1. Tim. 1. verſ. 19. Hee that thinketh hee ſtandeth, let him take heed leaſt he fall. 1. Cor. 10. ver. 12. Chriſt ſaith to the Angell of the Church of Epheſus. Thou haſt left thy firſt loue, Reue. 2. ver. 4. Take heede leaſt anie man fall away from the grace of God, Heb. 12. verſ. 15. And S. Peter doth ſpeake of ſuch as are like the dog that returneth to his vomite. 2. Pet. 2. There be other places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which they doe alſo alleadge to prooue that men that haue the true &amp; liuely faith, may wholy looſe it, I will not ſtand to anſwere euery one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularlie, but in generall, and thus, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the word of God ſpeaketh of falling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace, of turning from the way of righteouſnes, or loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the faith, it is not to bee vnderſtood of the grace of ſanctification or of the true liuely iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, but of that other faith which the holie ſcriptures doe ſpeake of, which the wicked may haue, and of thoſe graces which they alſo are after a ſort made partakers of. For this is ſufficient for me to ſhewe, that whoſoeuer is once partaker of
<pb facs="tcp:12478:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>the liuelie faith, he can neuer looſe that faith, hee can neuer periſh: for that being prooued it muſt needs be confeſled that all the ſcriptures which they alleadge are to bee vnderſtood not of that liuely faith, or of thoſe that be ſanctified. I am (ſaith Chriſt) the true vine, and my father is an husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Euery branch in me that beareth not fruite he taketh away, and euery branch in me that bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth fruite he purgeth that it may beare more fruit. Ioh. 15. verſ. 1.2. Chriſt is the vine, &amp; they which profeſſe his name be the bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches. Theſe branches be of two ſortes: the one ſort beareth no fruit, the other ſort beareth fruit. Now let it bee demanded what are they which beare fruit? It muſt needs be anſwered, they be ſuch as haue the true and liuely faith, they be ingrafted into Chriſt and doe receiue as it were the ſap or iuice of life from him. Their faith is that, which Saint Paule ſaith, worketh by charity, and therfore euery one that hath that faith beareth fruite. Then who bee thoſe branches that beare not fruite? They be Chriſtians in name and in profeſſion; otherwiſe he would not ſay, Euerie branch in me that beareth not fruit. They be after a ſort grafted alſo into Chriſt in as much as they haue been baptized, and doe profeſſe to beleeue in him: but their faith is but a dead faith; otherwiſe it could not be ſaide, that they beare no fruite. By this we ſee it is euident that there is a difference of faith, there is a fruitleſſe or a dead faith, and there is a faith which is liuely, and cannot but worke. Then ſee how we are to argue out of this place.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12478:33"/>Euery branch that beareth fruit, that is, euery one that hath the true and liuely faith, ſhall be purged, that it may beare more fruit: therefore not any one of the reprobate haue the liuely faith. This conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is cleere, if wee conſider that he ſaith, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie branch that beareth fruit he purgeth, not to take it afterward away, but that it may bear more fruit. For will they be ſo bold as to ſay thus, Some branches that beare fruite ſhall bee taken out of the vine, as well as the branches that beare no fruite? Or thus, Some branches that beare fruite ſhall be purged that they may beare more fruite: but yet in the end they ſhall alſo bee taken out of the vine, were not that a ſtrange ſpeech? What difference, or what a vaine difference were that which Chriſt maketh of the branches, touching perſeuerance in the vine if the fruitfull branches, or any of them could be ſeparated from it, as well as the vnfruitfull? howe doe they make Chriſt to ſpeak? It may be they wil ſay, that the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaketh ſomtimes vnſuerſally, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions in particulars are for to be admitted: and ſo his ſaying doth ſtand true although ſome bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that haue born fruit, be taken out of the vine and do periſh. I anſwere, that this cauill is of no force heer becauſe ourSauiour doth ſo ſpeak vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſallie, that he alſo ſpeaketh ſingularly. He ſaith not al the branches that in me bear fruit, but euery branch in me that beareth fruit, he purgeth that it may beare more fruit. So that we may conclude, that there are none of the reprobate that haue the
<pb facs="tcp:12478:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>true and liuely faith: for if they had, they ſhoulde bring forth fruit and ſo remain for euer in the vine. Againe, whoſoeuer knoweth that hee bringeth foorth fruite, hee may be aſſured that he ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the vine for euer, hee ſhall neuer periſh. Alſo Chriſt ſaith, I am the breade of life, hee that commeth to me ſhall not hunger in any wiſe, and he that beleeueth in mee ſhall neuer thirſt. This is the will of him that ſent me, that euery one that ſeeth the ſonne and beleeueth in him may haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life: and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt day. I am that bread of life, your fathers did eate Manna in the wilderneſſe and are dead. This is that bread that came downe from heauen, that if anie man eate thereof, he ſhould not die. I am the liuing bread which came downe from heauen, if any man eate of this bread he ſhall liue for euer. He that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood hath eternall life: This is that bread which came downe from heauen, not as your fathers did eate Manna, and are dead: he that eateth of this bread ſhall liue for euer. Ioh. 6. ver. 35.40.48.49 50.51.54.58. From theſe Scriptures wee may drawe moſt firme concluſions, that not any one of the reprobate euer haue or can haue the true and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie faith: but that whoſoeuer beleeueth he is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of life eternall: Chriſt teacheth that hee is the bread of life, and that whoſoeuer eateth of that bread he ſhall liue for euer. It is not poſſible that any man ſhould eat of that bread, and yet not liue for euer. Euery one that beleeueth in him (I ſpeak
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12478:34"/>of that liuelie faith which as the hand apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Chriſt, and by which we receiue him and his benefites) doth eat his fleſh, and drinke his blood. He that beleeueth in mee (ſaith hee) ſhall neuer thirſt: for let any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew a reaſon why ſome that beleeue in Chriſt doe eate his fleſh and drinke his blood &amp; other ſome, hauing the ſame liuely faith, doe not. What will they ſay that the reprobate &amp; damned, ſo many of them as euer come to haue the true and liuely faith (according as they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) do indeede eat the fleſh of Chriſt &amp; drinke his blood, and ſo for a time be made liuely mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, euen fleſh of his fleſh, and bones of his bones, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh Epheſ. 5. ver. 31? If they doe not eat his fleſh &amp; drink his blood, then haue they not the faith: remooue that effect, and the cauſe is remooued. If they will not abhor ſo wicked a ſpeech, but affirm indeed that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate doe eate the fleſh of Chriſt, ſo many of them as haue the liuely faith: then let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee how they ouerthrow alſo the whole force of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt, by which he proueth that the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na was not the bread of life; but that he himſelf is the bread of life. Your fathers (ſaith he) did eat Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in the wilderneſſe and are dead. If any man eat of this bread he ſhal liue for euer. How ſtandeth his argument, conſider of it I pray you. Your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did eat Manna in the wilderneſſe, and yet are dead in their ſinnes: they are dead in the ſpirituall and eternall death (for of that death hee ſpeaketh, ſeeing they alſo which eat the fleſh of Chriſt doe
<pb facs="tcp:12478:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>die the naturall death) therefore Manna was not the bread of life that commeth downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For that which ſome did eat of, and yet did die eternallie, is not by any meanes the bread of life. And how doth hee prooue that hee himſelfe is the bread of life? I am the breade which came downe from heauen: if any man eate of this bread he ſhall liue for euer. Thus ſtandeth his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Whoſoeuer eateth the fleſh of Chriſt, he ſhal liue for euer: therefore the fleſh of Chriſt is the bread of life. If they ſhall now ſay, ſome of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the wildernes did eate the Manna, and yet died in their ſinnes: it cannot be denied: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Chriſt doth affirme that Manna was not the bread of life that commeth downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and then adde their owne ſaying, which is this, ſome doe eate the fleſh of Chriſt, and yet do die in their ſinnes: what will then followe? if this reaſon do ſtand in force; Your fathers did eat Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in the wildernes and are dead: therefore Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na was not the bread of life. Then ſhall not this alſo follow, Many doe eat the fleſh of Chriſt, and yet are damned: therefore the fleſh of Chriſt is not the bread of life. Thus it is euident that ſuch as do affirme that any of the reprobate haue the liuelie faith, doe gainſay Chriſt, and ouerthrow the force of his argument.</p>
               <p>To proceede, what can be more firme to proue that the reprobate cannot haue the true, liuely and iuſtifying faith, then that which Saint Paul hath written? Where this ground is firſt to bee laide,
<pb facs="tcp:12478:35"/>that whoſoeuer he is that hath the true iuſtifying faith, he hath the ſpirite of ſanctification, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of adoption: for thus the Apoſtle conioyneth them: wherein alſo after that yee beleeued, yee were ſealed with the holy ſpirit of promiſe, which is the earneſt of our inheritance, vnto the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the purchaſed poſſeſſion, vnto the praiſe of his glorie: Epheſ. 1. ver. 13.14. Is there any ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd as to hold that a man is a liuely member of Ieſus Chriſt (as euery one is that hath the liuelie iuſtifying faith) and yet hath not that holy ſpirite of promiſe, that ſpirite of adoption, that ſcale, and that pledge? If they will ſay that the faith which the reprobate doe attaine vnto is without this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of adoption, or without this ſeale or pledge: then doe wee holde with them, and then doth it follow, that the faith of the reprobate is not the true iuſtifying and ſanctifying ſaith which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the heart, Act. 15. But if they ſhall ſay that the reprobate are for a time partakers of the ſpirit of ſanctification, euen of that ſpirit of adoption: then will there diuers right wicked conſequences follow, which are to be baniſhed far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For firſt touching the ſpirit of adoption, ſee what the Apoſtle ſaith; As manie as are led by the ſpirit of god, they are the ſons of God. For ye haue not receiued the ſpirit of bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage again to fear; but ye haue receiued the ſpirit of Adoption, whereby we crie Abba, Father. That ſame ſpirite beareth witneſſe vnto our ſpirit that we are the ſonnes of God. Rom. 8.14, 15, 16. If anie of the reprobate be led by the ſpirit of God, or be at anie time ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,
<pb facs="tcp:12478:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>then hath not S. Paule here ſaid true, that as manie as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the ſonnes of God. Some of the reprobate indeed doe taſte of the heauenly power, but they are not led with the ſpirit of God: they be not ſanctified, they walke not after the ſpirit. Moreouer, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of adoption, the ſanctifying ſpirit which is in al that haue the true, liuely and iuſtifying faith, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth withes with and to the ſpirit of the beleeuers, that they be the children of God. This is the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith when a man beleeueth that the Lorde God is his father, and that he is the ſonne of God. And this faith is not ſeparated from the ſpirit of adoption, for it is vpon his teſtimonie that they do beleeue, and by him they crie Abba, Father. Is not this ſpirit a true ſpirit? and is not his witnes moſt firme andtrue? If it be as thoſe men ſay, that the reprobate are partakers of the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then is not his teſtimonie firme and true. For then that ſpirit of adoption teacheth ſome man to call God Father, and witneſſeth to his ſpirit that he is the ſonne of God, when as he is the childe of the diuell: for hauing that faith, and that teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the ſpirit in him to day, to morrow he doth by their ſaying, vtterly and ſinally loſe that faith and that ſpirit. What an opinion is this to ſay that a man hath the true faith, that is to ſay, beleeueth by the teſtimony of the holy Ghoſt, that God is his father, and yet he is indeed the child of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell? And moreouer, doth not the Apoſtle ſay, that after they beleeued they were ſcaled with the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12478:36"/>holie ſpirit of promiſe? This is more then the bare teſtimonie of the ſpirit, if I may ſo ſpeake, that hee ſealeth. Can this ſeale be diſanulled or broken, or made fruſtrate? Is this ſeale vntrue? If it bee euer ſet vpon the reprobate, it is deceiueable. If their opinion be true: no man can then ſay thus, God hath ſealed me with his ſpirit, therfore I doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God: For a reprobate hath that ſeale, and it faileth him: then who can ſay that it is a ſeale, which is true and infallible? Saint Iohn ſhewing vpon what teſtimonies faith in Chriſt is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: ſaith, There be three that bear record in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the Father, the Word, and the holie Spirit, and theſe three are one. And there bee three that bear record in earth, the ſpirit, &amp; water &amp; blood, and theſe three agree in one. If we receiue the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of men, the teſtimonie of God is greater: For this is the witnes which hee teſtifieth of his ſonne. Hee that beleeueth in the ſonne of God, hath the witneſſe in himſelfe. 1. Ioh. 5. verſ. 7.8.9.10. Why are all theſe witneſſes but to giue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of faith? And if theſe witneſſes doe teſtifie vnto a man that he is the childe of God and ſhall be ſaued (for euery one that hath the true &amp; liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie faith, hath it vpon the teſtimony of all theſe witneſſes) and yet hee is a reprobate: then is not the witneſſe of God greater then the witneſſe of men. Then alſo to what end ſhould be mention all theſe foreſaid witneſſes? They giue an abſolute teſtimonie that euery one that beleeueth hath life euerlaſting.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12478:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> By theſe places it is manifeſt that the reprobate cannot be partakers of the ſanctifying faith, they be not led at any time by the ſpirit of adoption, they be not ſealed vp with the holy ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, they haue not the witneſſe of God within them: whoſoeuer therefore hath theſe thinges, let him be aſſured he ſhall neuer periſh but if he be ſanctified, he is iuſtified, hee ſhall bee glorified. Rom. 8. ver. 32. And this is it which the holie Scripture in many places proclameth, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beieeueth in the ſonne of God, he ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be confounded.</p>
               <p>But what if the reprobate neuer haue the true faith, nor the ſpirit of adoption? yet doe not the elect ſo fall and ſinne ſometimes, that there is no ſparke of true faith left in them for the time? This is the great cunning of the diuell to roote vp as it were the ſiableneſſe and foundation of the truth. But the word of God meeteth with it, and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that whoſoeuer is regenerate and borne of God in the new &amp; ſpirituall birth, as euery one is that hath the liuely faith, ſeeing whoſoeuer is in Chriſt, he is a new creature: the ſame man cannot ſo fall that this new birth ſhould be extinguiſhed in him. For this wee haue the teſtimonie vttered by Saint Iohn, in theſe words, Whoſoeuer is born of god ſinneth not, for his ſeed remaineth in him, neither can he ſinne, becauſe hee is borne of God. 1. Ioh. 3. ver. 9. Alſo, we know that whoſoeuer is borne of God ſinneth not, but he that is begotten of God keepeth himſelfe, and that wicked one
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:12478:37"/>doth not touch him. chap. 5. verſ. 18. In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe two ſayings, there be two members, and vnto either of them, there is annexed a reaſon to confirme the ſame. As whoſoeuer is borne of God ſinneth not: for his ſeede (this is the reaſon) remaineth in him. And then the ſecond member, Neither can hee ſinne: the reaſon, becauſe hee is borne of God. Now ſee if they doe not directlie gainſay the holie Ghoſt, which holde that a man regenerate may looſe the faith, &amp; be vtterly voide of the ſpirit of ſanctification. For firſt, whereas S. Iohn ſaith, that whoſoeuer is born of God, he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not. They ſay, a man hath his faith vtterhe quenched, and is wholie depriued of the ſpirit of adoption. What ſin then is it that he ſinneth not? He that falleth in ſuch ſort as that he becommeth void of the true faith, and of the ſanctifying grace of God, what is he other but as an infidell for the time, and what ſinne is it that he committeth not? Shall it be ſaid of ſuch a man, he ſinneth not? It may be this poore cauill will be vſed, Hee that is borne of God ſinneth not ſo long as he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in that eſtate, ſo long as he continueth borne of God. A vaine and moſt fooliſh ſpeech, for if a man that is vnregenerate and borne of GOD through a true and liuelie faith, do ſo fal, it is ſinne that caſteth him downe, then he doth ſinne while he is in that ſtate. For doth hee firſt caſt away his faith, and the grace of the ſanctifying ſpirit, and then commit ſinne, and not before? What greater ſinne then the falling from the faith, and caſting
<pb facs="tcp:12478:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>forth vtterlie the grace of ſanctification? But ſee how Saint Iohn meeteth with all cauilles, in the reaſon which he annexeth to confirme that firſt member. Why doth not any one that is borne of God, ſinne? For (ſaith hee) his ſeede remaineth in him. What is the ſeed of God which remaineth in all that are borne of God? The word of God is called the incorruptible ſeed by which God doth beget his children, 1 Pet. 1.23. That word is but an inſtrument, the holie Ghoſt is the worker of the new birth: and therfore our Sauiour teacheth, except a man bee borne againe of water and of the ſpirit, hee cannot enter into the kingdome of God. Ioh. 3. verſ 5. The ſeed of God then is the graces of the ſanctifying ſpirit, &amp; the liuely word. Thoſe men that ſay, a man may loſe his faith, and the ſpirit of ſanctification, doe in flat ſpeech con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie that which the holie Apoſtle heere ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. The ſeed of God (ſaith Saint Iohn) remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in all thoſe which are borne of God, and therfore they doe not ſinne, that is to ſay, they do not ſinne that deadly ſinne of falling from God, or of being ſeparated from Chriſt: which is not true if their ſaying bee true: for there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no ſeed of God in thoſe that doe wholy loſe their faith, and in whome the ſanctifying graces are vtterly extinguiſhed. It may be they wil here again adde their vaine cauill, that the ſeed of God remaineth in them ſo long as they bee borne of God, and hold the faith, and ſtand in grace. As it Saint Iohn ſhould ſay thus, the ſeede of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:12478:38"/>in them, ſo long as the ſeede of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in them. Is not this a very wiſe ſpeech to be aſcribed to the holy ghoſt? He ſpeaketh abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, that whoſoeuer is borne of God, the ſeed of God euer after doth remaine in him: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſinneth not. Let them go with their ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous diſtinction, the feed of God remaineth in them, ſo long as it remaineth in them: for that ſpeech they muſt be forced to vtter, vnleſſe they will confeſſe, that when he ſaith his ſeede remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in them, we muſt take it remaineth in them for euer. If the ſeede of God remaine for euer in the regenerate, then doth ſaith and the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit remaine in them for euer. For will they ſeparate theſe? But to put all out of doubt, and to miniſter ſound comfort, or (as the holy ghoſt ſpeaketh) ſtrong conſolation to all that haue the true and liuely faith, euen to let them knowe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and vnderſtand for certainty, that they can not periſh, that they cannot be ouercome by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan in the battel: he addeth, Neither can he ſinne: confirming it with this reaſon, becauſe he is born of God. What can they ſay vnto this? How will they auoide this? Will they ſay that Saint Iohn meant heere ſome other matter? Is it not clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then the Sunne, that the regenerate cannot wholy bee depriued of faith, nor of the ſpirit of ſanctification, when he ſaith, they can not ſinne? Can they wholie looſe their faith and all the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying grace, and yet can they not ſin? O how happie and bleſſed is the ſtate and condition of
<pb facs="tcp:12478:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>that man which hath attained to the true &amp; liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie faith, who hath the ſpirit of ſanctification, by which hee is led, euen the ſpirit of adoption that beareth witneſſe with his ſpirit that he is the child of God, ſeeing he may be tempted, and ſundrie times be led a wrie into ſome ſinnes, but it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that he ſhuld fall from God? And what is the reaſon by which he prooueth that hee cannot ſo fall: Becauſe (ſaith he) he is borne of God. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider where the force of this reaſon lieth. Men are mortall, their ſeede is corruptible, and that which is borne of man is corruptible and mortall. God is incorruptible and immortall, and ſo the ſeede of God is called incorruptible ſeed and immortal: whereupon it doth follow that the birth which is of God is incorruptible and immortall. Where the life of God is, it cannot bee be extinguiſhed. Thinke it not ſtrange then that Saint Iohn ſaith, he cannot ſinne, becauſe he is borne of God. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they will denie the manifeſt and cleare te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the word of God: except they will affirme that the ſeed of God is corruptible and ſo decayeth, and doth not abide in thoſe that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of God: except they will alſo make the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of the ſpirit of adoption deceiueable &amp; falſe: finally, except they will make the ſeale of God and the pledge which he giueth, of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, denying that men are to make their calling and election ſure, and ſo to haue ſtrong conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let them renounce this Popiſh errour, that the true and liuely faith, and the ſanctifying ſpirit
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12478:39"/>may be in the reprobate, and that the ſame liuelie faith &amp; quickening grace may be wholie put out for a time in the elect. It may bee demanded that ſeeing the word of God is ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that men are to reſiſt the diuel ſtedfaſt in the faith, as being fully aſſured that he which hath once attained the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith can neuer be ouercome nor periſh: what ſhuld be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe that ſome do hold that true faith &amp; the ſpirit of adoption may be had &amp; loſt again? What ſhould caſt them vpon ſuch rocks, or driue them into ſuch abſurdities? Surely they be driuen into theſe while they do (as they ſuppoſe) eſchue more da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous rocks, &amp; greater abſurdities. They would haue it to be ſomwhat in mans own wil &amp; power to receiue faith &amp; the whole work of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They wold haue it be in the power &amp; wil of man to retain the ſame faith &amp; ſanctifying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit &amp; to loſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Why are they of that mind? Is it becauſe they enuy, that god ſhuld haue the whole praiſe &amp; glory of mans ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as man being not able to doe any thing the grace is wholy of God? We cannot ſay ſo. But it is another thing that dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them hereunto: &amp; that is this: they take it that vnles it be in mans wil &amp; power to receiue and to retain faith, it wil follow from an higher cauſe, &amp; that is this: namely that ſuch as God hath choſen vnto life, to thoſe he giueth faith &amp; worketh in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his ſpirit the new birth. Then the other ſort (if there be no power in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not attain to the faith &amp; regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they be before ordained vnto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deſtruction. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil it follow that there is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:12478:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an eternal decree of God, by which he hath choſen and ordained ſome to life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and appointed others to eternall deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This doctrine they ſay chargeth God with iniuſtice &amp; with crueltie. For what is more cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell then of purpoſe to create and make any of his workes or creatures to be condemned vnto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall torments? Where is then (ſay they) the infinit mercie, iuſtice and goodneſſe of God? To charge the Lorde God with any crueltie or iniuſtice, is moſt wicked, blaſphemous and abominable. And therefore they hold this the moſt ſafe courſe for the defence of the iuſtice and mercy of God, where the word of God ſpeaketh of election, to take it thus, that GOD hath choſen vnto life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall all thoſe whome he did foreſee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the faith, walke in obedience and continue to the end, and ſo their faith, good works and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance which God foreſaw, is the cauſe that mooued the Lord to chooſe them. On the other ſide, that he hath not reprobate any, but hee hath foreſeene that they either woulde not receiue the faith at al, or els after they haue receiued it, of their owne wickednes fall from it vtterly and finally, and ſo he hath before ordained them in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge vnto damnation. This they ſay ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with reaſon, the other they hold to be repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to reaſon. What ſhall we ſay to this? ſhall wee heere enter for to diſcourſe at large by the ſcriptures touching election and reprobation? I haue no ſuch purpoſe. But only ſo farre as agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12478:40"/>with our preſent matter, namely to make it appeare, that the ſtedfaſtneſſe of our faith, and the full aſſurance of our ſaluation, dependeth vpon the knowledge of our election. As namely, if wee finde in vs the true and liuely faith, which goeth with the ſpirit of ſanctification, wee may then riſe vp to that high cauſe, and be aſſured that the Lord hath in that his eternall and vnchangeable decree choſen vs in Chriſt to be his children, ſo that wee cannot periſh.</p>
               <p>To come then to an anſwere to thoſe men: Is not this a ſtrange thing, that they will compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend by reaſon how God could decree the choiſe or election of ſome of his creatures vnto life, and the reprobation of others vnto eternall deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their ſinnes, and yet not vniuſt? If wee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage the ſentence of the Apoſtle, <hi>But who art thou O man that pleadeſt with God?</hi> They aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that they doe not pleade with God, but they ſtand for the defence of the iuſtice and mercie of God, leaſt that ſhuld be imputed vnto him which is vniuſt and cruell. No? Is not this to plead with God, or againſt God, when hee ſhall bee iuſt, hee ſhall be good, hee ſhall bee mercifull, no further than thy reaſon can comprehend? He muſt yeeld a reaſon vnto thy vnderſtanding and capacitie, with what right or equitie he could doe ſo, or ſo, or els thou wilt reiect it? Is not this I ſay, to plead againſt God? Saint Paule after hee hath diſputed of the reiecting of the Iewes, and the calling in of the Gentiles, breaketh foorth into this exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb facs="tcp:12478:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>O the deepneſſe of the riches both of the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and knowledge of God: how vnſearchable are his iudgments and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> Rom. 11. To this agreeth the Prophet in the Pſalm, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Thy iugdments are as the great deep.</hi> Let it be demanded, what iudgementes of God are thoſe which be vnſearchable, or which bee as the great deep? Are they not thoſe iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which he exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth vpon his creatures, and eſpecially vpon his chief creatures, Angels and men? If theſe his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be as the great deep, euen vnſearcheable &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible both vnto men and Angels, then is it ſo in the higheſt matter, namely that hee hath ordained by his eternall decree to beſtow eternall life and glory vpon ſome, and to appoint other ſome vnto eternal ignominie &amp; torments, which they ſhall endure iuſtly for their ſinnes: For if any iudgementes of God bee vnſearcheable, or any where, it is in predeſtination. It may bee rightlie ſaid, that if the counſels, and wayes, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God be not vnſearchable in that eternal decree; then is there no iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: which is to denie not only the ſaying of the Apoſtle and of the Prophet, but alſo after a ſort to denie God, for he that will make his iudgmentes to be ſearchable, maketh alſo God himſelfe to be ſearchable. Wilt thou meaſure and comprehend the counſels, the decrees, and the iudgementes of God by reaſon? Then meaſure and comprehend God himſelfe, euen that eternall and infinit maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, with thy reaſon. Nowe if it bee ſo, that God
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12478:41"/>hath choſen ſome for this cauſe that he did foreſee that of their owne wil and power they would be faithfull, do good works &amp; continue to the ende. And on the other ſide, that hee did foreſee who would be vnfaithfull, wicked, and rebellious euen to their death, and thoſe in his foreknowledge he ſaw to be iuſtly damned. Here is nothing incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible in theſe iudgmentes. For thy reaſon doth find out, and thy vnderſtanding doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all cauſes, and thou canſt ſhew a reaſon how God hath done euery thing, and yet is iuſt: yea all the cauſes of his counſelles he open vnto thee, if it bee ſo. Why then did Saint Paule crie out. <hi>How vnſearchable are his iudgments!</hi> Why faith the Prophet alſo. <hi>That they be a great deepe?</hi> The Prophet was dull of conceipt (it ſeemeth) and ſo was Paule: for thou haſt entred into this great deepe, and haſt with the light of thy reaſon ſearched out all things, and whatſoeuer is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the ſame thy reaſon, thou doubteſt not to daſh it out of Gods decrees. Thou wilt haue nothing to ſtand higher then thy reaſon can reach vnto and comprehende. Thou ſaieſt that whatſoeuer is contrarie vnto reaſon is abſurde. Well, but take heede that thou doeſt not extoll reaſon too much. It doth indeed comprehend the principles of logicke: but that it will from thence riſe vp to comprehend God, and his eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, it is extreame folly. If wee looke a little in particulars, we ſhall find it to bee ſo. VVe do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and confeſſe that the Lord God by his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:12478:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>power &amp; infinit wiſedom created heauen &amp; earth, &amp; al things which are in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both viſible &amp; inuiſible. Of the inuiſible creatures in heauen, the Angels, ſome ſinned &amp; fel, whom he hath conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto eternall fire: they be now diuels. Others (whom the holie Apoſtle calleth the elect An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) neuer ſinned, neither ſhall euer any of them ſinne, as they bee well aſſured, but ſhall remaine verie glorious and bleſſed for euer.</p>
               <p>Tell me nowe, were not all theſe the creatures of God, and created in the ſame eſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? How commeth it that ſome of them ſtand, &amp; others do fall? Will ye not ſay that of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodneſſe and loue, hee had decreed to ſtay vp the one parte, ſo that they ſhould neuer ſinne, nor be in danger of falling: and that he had alſo decreed to leaue thoſe other to their owne will and power? why did he not ſhew the ſame good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and loue towards all? whie did he ſet ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious creatures in ſuch eſtate, as that they ſhould fal from the heauenlie glory into diuels torments? was he not able to ſupport them, and to retaine them in glory with the reſt? He created man in great dignitie, euen after his owne image; whie did he not keepe him in that eſtate? why did hee ſuffer the diuell to enter in vnto the woman and to tempt her? why did hee not forewarn the man and the woman, that ſuch an enemie woulde ſet vpon them? or why did he not giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrength to get the victorie in that te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation? O wilt thou ſay, God did only ſuffer thoſe thinges to bee done
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:12478:42"/>by the diuell: hee did not ordaine that any ſuch matter ſhould fall out: for that cannot ſtand with equity or iuſtice: it agreeth not with mercy. Wel, thou haſt a childe, and when it is in thy power to let, yet thou wittinglie doeſt ſuffer a terrible Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to enter in vnto him and to deuour him: who will ſay that this is a ſufficient excuſe to cleer thee from crueltie: to ſay that thou didſt not decree it, but onlie ſuffer it to come ſo to paſſe? If this bee no excuſe to defend thee, how fooliſh art thou in vſing it to defende the iuſtice and mercie of God? VVilt thou thus call the iuſtice of God and his mercie vnder the account of thy reaſon, that thou maiſt by thine owne wit comprehend it, or els it cannot bee iuſtice? O howe much better is it that thou ſhouldeſt crie out with the Apoſtle, <hi>How vnſearchable are his iudgmentes!</hi> And where thou canſt not comprehend by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon howe God ſhoulde in iuſtice either decree or ſuffer the fall of Angels and men; yet to reſt in this, that howſoeuer wee cannot comprehende thoſe thinges, yet we are ſure that there can be no vnrighteouſnes with God: but whatſoeuer he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeth, it is moſt holie and iuſt, for his will is the perfect rule of all righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>To proceede, when man was fallen, and had caſt himſelfe and all his poſterity into endleſſe miſerie, a redeemer is promiſed. All are loſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, there be none which are in themſelues bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or more worthy than other, why then is not the redeemer ſent vnto all? If any ſhall replie and
<pb facs="tcp:12478:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſay hee was ſent vnto all: that is vntrue: for God choſe the ſeede of Abraham, the nation of the Iewes, he ſeparated them from al other nations of the world, he gaue them his lawes and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, euen the liuelie Oracles for to teach them. The other nations he left in the darke, to walke in the vanities of their owne minde, ſubiect to the manifold illuſions and ſleightes of diuelles, and that for manie ages together, among whome there were ſo manie famous wiſe men, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Poets and Orators. Yea there were among them infinit thouſand thouſands which could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hear of Chriſt, &amp; of infants dying and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their natiue corruption, that is, in originall ſinne. Who can ſearch out and comprehend the iudgmentes of God in this? were they not the worke of his handes? Yet there is no hope offred vnto them. But at the length Chriſt Ieſus, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly light and ſaluation of the worlde, is preached to the Gentiles. Why did hee not now open the eies of all? whie did he not giue that effectuall grace of his ſpirit vnto all as to beleeue in his ſon vnto ſaluation? VVhen hee opened the heart of Lydia, why did he not alſo open the heartes of the reſt that heard Paule preach? Some will ſay they would not. Yea but hee of thoſe that were moſt vnwilling made willing where it pleaſed him: As we haue a perfect example in Saint Paule, who was a cruell perſecuter. Chriſt ſaith, No man commeth vnto me, except the father which ſent me draw him. Ioh. 6. VVhy did hee not drawe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12478:43"/>Herode, and Pilate and the high Prieſtes, as well as Paule? VVee ſee in theſe latter dayes that there be great Nations, as the weſt Indies, which had neuer hearde of Chriſt vntill of late time, and then by a moſt cruell and idolatrous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which haue murthered them moſt wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſo that they haue been made to ſtumble and to bee further from Chriſt. VVho is able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the depth of theſe iudgementes? Shall not wee lay downe the pride of our owne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and ſay with the Apoſtle, Hath not the Potter power ouer the claie, of the ſame lumpe to make one veſſell vnto honour and an other vnto diſhonour? Or ſhall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, Whie haſt thou made me thus? O beloued, let vs lay aſide all ſuch vaine and curious preſumptions: and let vs, as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Scripture directeth vs make our ſingular comfort of that eternall decree of God. Thus wee are with it to fortifie our ſelues againſt the Diuell. God of his owne good will hath choſen in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, euen before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the worlde were laide, thoſe whome he will ſaue, as the heires of eternall glorie. Hee hath in his prefixed time redeemed them, not with golde or precious ſtones, (as Saint Peter ſaith) but with the blood of his ſonne, as of a Lambe immaculate and without ſpot. He doth alſo call them, hee doth ſanctifie them. This decree of God is vnchangeable, it is vnpoſsible that any of his elect ſhould periſh. VVho can
<pb facs="tcp:12478:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>plucke them out of the handes of Chriſt? Then in the next place wee are to bee aſſured that none can haue the true faith but the choſen of God. Not any doe receiue the ſpirit of adoption which witneſſe unto their ſpirit that they be the children of God but the elect. The elect are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie regenerate and borne of God, and ſealed with the holie ſpirit of promiſe.</p>
               <p>Then come downe to thy ſelfe: If thou canſt trulie ſay, I haue the liuelie faith, I haue receiued the ſpirit of adoption, which doth witneſſe with my ſpirit that I am the childe of God: I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, I haue the true repentance, I am ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified: Satan doth tempt mee ſtronglie manie wayes, but I am ſure, though he often as it were foile thee, and cauſe me to goe awrie, that hee ſhall neuer get the victorie ouer mee. Is not this a ſingular comfort to a man? If anie that hath the ſpirit of adoption may loſe him: then where is the ſtedfaſtneſſe of faith which Saint Peter heere requireth, in reſiſting the Diuel? If it come once to lie in our ſelues, wee cannot bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedlie ſure and ſtedfaſt: wee may well wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and doubt: but when we knowe that we are kept by the power of God, as it is written, 1. Pet. 1. Then haue wee a rocke whereon to reſt: then doe we ſtand ſtedfaſt armed with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God.</p>
               <p>This faith may be tried, and ſeeme oftentimes to be ſore ſhaken, but it can neuer bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12478:44"/>Yea, will ſome man ſay, but euery man cannot come to knowe that hee hath receiued the true and liuely faith, or the ſpirit of adoption, we ſee many goe farre in the profeſsion of the goſpel, and thinke that they haue the true faith, and the ſanctifying ſpirit, which yet fall quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. It is true that there bee manie which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the goſpell and profeſſe it with ſuch feeling that they ſuppoſe God hath called them as his children: there is for the time ſuch a touch &amp; ſuch a moouing in their heartes, and yet in time they manifeſt themſelues not to be of God. One oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion or other driueth them awrie, ſo that ſome of them become heretickes, ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, although they fall not into hereſies, yet they fall into vices, and become ſo irreligious, that all the former gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they had taſted of, doe vaniſh and are loſt. And this is the cauſe we are willed by Saint Peter to make our calling and election ſure. For ſeeing the reprobate receiue a kinde of faith and zeale, which yet is not the true and liuely faith, we are willed to be diligent and carefull to ſee that we reſt not in that faith. VVe muſt labour to attain to that teſtimonie of the ſpirit of adoption: we muſt ſeek to bee confirmed and euen ſealed with the holie ſpirit of promiſe, and ſo come to that full aſſurance of faith and hope which neuer confoundeth. And that is it which Saint Peter teacheth the way to come vnto, in the place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alleadged, where he willeth vs to ioine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb facs="tcp:12478:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>with our faith, with vertue knowledge, &amp;c. For if we follow that rule which hee there preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, we ſhall be ſure neuer to fall, we ſhall then with a ſtedfaſt faith reſiſt our aduerſarie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and get the victorie ouer him. It is a matter of great importance, I pray and beſeech you, as you tender the happy eſtate of your owne ſoules, looke vnto it. Set your hearts vpon the liuelie O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of God, and ſeeke day and night after the knowledge of holie thinges, and howe to pleaſe the Lord your God. Then ſhall you bee bleſſed for euermore, Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
